<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs counsel to his church in two sermons preached at the two last fasts : one April xi. MDCLXXX, the other December xxi. MDCLXXX / by Symon Patrick ...</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12301845</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12301845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 923:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs counsel to his church in two sermons preached at the two last fasts : one April xi. MDCLXXX, the other December xxi. MDCLXXX / by Symon Patrick ...</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 111 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Macock, for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II-III --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59159:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſts Counſel TO HIS CHURCH.</p>
            <p>IN TWO SERMONS Preached at the <hi>Two Laſt Faſts,</hi> ONE APRIL xi. MDCLXXIX.</p>
            <p>THE OTHER DECEMBER xxii. MDCLXXX.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SYMON PATRICK,</hi> D. D. DEAN of <hi>PETERB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Macock,</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to His Moſt Sacred Majeſty. 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59159:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59159:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable WILLIAM EARL of <hi>BEDFORD,</hi> Knight of the Moſt Noble Order of the GARTER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">My very good LORD and PATRON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing deſired by ſome in my Pariſh to print the Sermon I preached on the laſt Faſt-day, I found it neceſſary to prefix to it the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon I preacht the Faſt before; becauſe this depends on that: and have preſumed to prefix Your Lordſhips Name to both; becauſe it is by Your Favour and Patronage, that I preached either the one or the other in that Place.</p>
            <p>The matter of them is ſuitable to the occaſion: For in the Firſt I have chiefly preſſed the General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of all the evils under which we labour; in the
<pb facs="tcp:59159:3"/>Second one Particular Remedy; and in both expoſed the wickedneſs of Popery. But I have ſhown withal, that all we ſay againſt it, will not keep it out: unleſs we will ſo duly prize our own Religion, as to live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it. Which being in the general allowed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by thoſe who continue to live quite contrary, I ſee no reaſon why any Body ſhould quarrel with what I have ſaid, about one particular Duty of our Religion: unleſs they think that we have nothing to anſwer for, upon the account of our contempt of Chriſts Miniſters, and of that Order which He hath appointed in His Church; which ſeems to me ſuch a dangerous ſin, that I could not think I diſcharged a good Conſcience, if at ſuch a time and ſuch an occaſion, I took no notice of it.</p>
            <p>Wherein I do not plead our own Cauſe, as ſome are wont to object to ſuch Diſcourſes, but the Cauſe of Chriſt and of His Religion: which now lyes a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and we fear a dying, by the wounds we give it our ſelves, through the ſubtile Contrivance of our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Adverſaries. Whoſe Plots have been many and horrid; but their firſt and greateſt ſtrength (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the directions given to their Emiſſaries) lay in this, To bring the whole Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> into contempt; and to divide the People from their eſtabliſhed Paſtors, into a great many little Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, under no Government but what they themſelves pleaſed. And it is apparent, that by the ſame Popiſh artifice, this poyſonous conceit is induſtriouſly infuſed
<pb facs="tcp:59159:3"/>into the peoples mind; that we are looking towards <hi>Rome,</hi> if we do but tell them, that they ought not to form opinions as they think good, but guide themſelves in their judgment by our direction.</p>
            <p>But I hope the better ſort are not ignorant, by this time, of their devices: and that though there be ſome in the Miniſtry who are not ſo fit as they ſhould be, to direct and guide their Flocks; yet they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the men who moſt complain of it are ſuch, as will be guided by none at all; no not by thoſe whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and honeſty cannot be ſuſpected. And it is a very great Truth alſo, that their intemperate Speeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy, is the thing that hath frighted the weaker ſort of them into ſuch an apprehenſion of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from thoſe men; as hath made them guilty of the follies which have done great injury to us all.</p>
            <p>This, My Lord, is the grief of all good Men among us, who conſider the ſtate we are in; and deſine the ſafety, or have any love for the honour, of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For we ſeem now to be in ſuch a condition as <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> deſcribes in his days: when things were come to ſuch a paſs, that the people neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood themſelves, from their own inward ſenſe, what was fit for them, nor would believe thoſe that rightly informed them. <hi>No,</hi> ſaith he<note n="*" place="margin">Tom. 2. p. 745. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, We are exceeding angry at our Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and very hardly bear their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions: their counſels are a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance;
<pb facs="tcp:59159:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59159:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59159:5"/>and their inſtruction in good things, we nauſeate, as ſick men do the medicines which their Phyſicians exhibite to them. If a reproof be given, we take it heavily; if we hear a rougher word, we fall into a rage; if we be thruſt out of the Church, we blaſpheme. This is not the diſpoſition of Learners, nor the obedience of Diſciples: but the ambitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of ſeditious and rebellious people. For a Scholar, who deſires to learn any common Art or Science, ought to be like a little Child: much more ought he to be like a ſucking Infant, who would be inſtructed in Chriſtian piety; becauſe our Lord hath honoured that Age, as apt to receive impreſſions, with his commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now no Child riſes up againſt the Characters and the Lineaments, that his Maſter makes for him in Wax; nor deviſes new Elements, by a frantick Licence innovating about making Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but exerciſes his hand after his Maſters Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and both in word and deed imitates what his Director delivers to him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth not thus; though he hath heard,</hi> That except ye be converted and become like little Children, ye cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: <hi>but when the Prieſt ſeverely corrects his errour, openly contradicts; and mutters between his teeth;
<pb facs="tcp:59159:5"/>and going round the Streets, and the places of publick concourſe, rails and reviles; and</hi> (as it follows a little after) <hi>ſits judging even me the Biſhop in the Chair of the Scorner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what can the end of ſuch things be, but utter confuſion? Which neceſſarily follows, when the unity that ought to be between the Paſtors and people is quite diſſolved; or the people (ſome upon one account, ſome upon another) loſe all their reſpect for them, and love to them for their works ſake.</p>
            <p>There hath been much ſpeech, Your Lordſhip knows, of a Prophecy (as it is called) of Biſhop <hi>Uſher,</hi> late Primate of <hi>Armagh;</hi> which hath very much ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many, and made them fear dreadful things: Though the certainty of it hath not been ſo publickly atteſted, as that which I have been bold to ſet down in the firſt of theſe Sermons. Where Your Lordſhip will find ſomething that looks like a ſad Prediction; which an excellent Divine and holy Man of this Church publiſhed long ago, in a Book of his upon the Creed. Which I wiſh were diligently heeded and laid to heart: becauſe it directs to the way, whereby the threatning may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided; pointing to the very ſin that deſerves the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he denounces. Which if it be ſlighted, when we are told of it; it will be one of the worſt ſigns that can be, his Prognoſtication will prove true and be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</p>
            <p>But they who are appointed to ſtand on the Watch-Tower,
<pb facs="tcp:59159:6"/>and give notice of danger, have delivered their own Souls; when they have faithfully declared the mind of Chriſt in this matter. Which was the greateſt motive I had both to preach and to print theſe Sermons; which I am ſure will be acceptable to Your Lordſhip: not only becauſe you have a due reſpect to Gods Miniſters; but becauſe I preſent them as a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of my gratitude, and of the honour I have for Your Lordſhip, being</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, S. PATRICK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59159:6"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED ON THE FAST-DAY, APRIL xi. MDCLXXIX.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. II. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Repent, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and I will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHAT our Saviour had ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Jews</hi> before his death, (in the Second Leſſon for this Morning Prayer) xiii. <hi>Luke</hi> 3, 5. <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh;</hi> He ſaith here (in effect) after his aſcenſion to Heaven, unto the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come quickly, and will fight againſt them with the ſword of any mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59159:7"/>
This is a Leſſon for all Nations, and for all Ages: in which the Church of <hi>England</hi> is as much concerned now, as the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> was then. Though this Letter was not particularly directed unto us, no more than to the reſt of the Chriſtian World; yet the next words tell us, that our Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects every body ſhould take notice of it, conſider it, and take warning by it, as much as if it had been addreſſed to them by name, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> We all herein read our own doom; and ought to underſtand the words as if our Lord had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged them in ſuch a general Admonition, as he gives in another caſe about watching, xiii. <hi>Mark ult. And what I ſay unto the Church of Pergamus, I ſay unto all, Repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come quickly, and will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words you may eaſily diſcern, An <hi>Exhortation</hi> to a moſt neceſſary Duty, which is, <hi>To repent:</hi> and a <hi>Commination</hi> in caſe the Exhortation be not obeyed; which is, A denunciation of war againſt ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Offenders, who provoke him to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59159:7"/>ſharpen againſt them, <hi>the ſword of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Exhortation is ſo frequently preſſed, and as frequently explained, that I cannot think it fit to ſpend the time in telling you what it is <hi>to repent.</hi> For you all know well enough, that it is <hi>ſuch a godly ſorrow for what we have done amiſs, as makes us not only afflict our ſelves for our ſins, but utterly renounce and forſake them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you know your Baptiſmal Vow (as who is there that can be unacquainted with it, unleſs he affect a ſtupid and brutiſh igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) it is eaſie to underſtand that nothing leſs than this can paſs with God for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>If we had never broken that Vow, there would have been no need of Repentance; which is the repairing of that breach, and the making it up again. And how ſhall we make all whole; but only by obſerving that Vow better, which we have violated and broken? No man of ſenſe can think, there is any other way of being reconciled to God after we have offended him; but only by becoming more dutiful to him: Performing, that is, thoſe engagements which we always
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59159:8"/>had to him, and from which we can never be abſolved; becauſe, beſide our natural obligation, we have tyed and bound our ſelves by a ſolemn and moſt ſacred Vow, to be his faithful Servants. When we do not keep this Vow we ſin, and bring a heavy guilt upon our ſelves. From which ſin and guilt, if we would be freed, we muſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> that is, keep our Vow better; forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Devil, and all his works; heartily believing God's holy Word; and obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keeping his Commandments. If we be truly ſorrowful and afflicted that we have not done thus; in which Repentance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins: we muſt reſolve and ſeriouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make this our buſineſs hereafter; in which Repentance ends and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more in ſo plain a buſineſs; which hath been urged upon you a thouſand times: not by one alone, but by all God's Miniſters that ever you heard preach about it. And what Theme is there more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that comes oftner into the Pulpits? I wiſh the perpetual ſound of it without due regard, have not made it become ſo ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, that now men turn a deaf ear to ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59159:8"/>Diſcourſes, as beaten and thredbare Subjects, to which they need not give any attendance. But if any man have an ear ſtill open; let him <hi>hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches,</hi> here in this Book. Let him hear, at leaſt, what a deſperate courſe he runs, if he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to neglect a Duty which is ſo well known, that he thinks he need not hear of it any more. For our Saviour threatens ſuch as would not repent, that he would <hi>come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them quickly, and fight againſt them with the ſword of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Motive you know to a change, is commonly an apprehenſion of the danger of that courſe, wherein a man is at preſent engaged. This is apt to put a ſtop unto him in his way, and bring him to a ſtand. The very firſt ſight of it, when it ſmites his Soul, is wont to repreſs the violence and heat wherewith he purſues his ſinful deſires. A new ſcene of thoughts begin to appear in his mind: and he is led to conſider with himſelf, <hi>Whither am I going? What miſchief is this which threatens me? Whither will this courſe carry me? and what will be the end of theſe things?</hi> And if the danger be very great and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59159:9"/>and his apprehenſion of it alſo be great and proportionable to the danger; this ſtrikes the greater fear and dread into his Soul. And fear of what will inſue, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes him to a change and alteration of his courſe of life; that he may eſcape thoſe miſeries which he ſees he is drawing upon himſelf. Eſpecially if he be perſwaded (as you have often heard) that no terrours or affrightments, no entreaties or prayers, no crys or tears, no ſadneſs or affliction of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, no outward humiliation or abaſements, no purpoſes, no promiſes will prevail for his deliverance from that danger; without an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual reformation and forſaking thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ways, that neceſſarily lead to death and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And it is no hard matter, one would think, for men to convince themſelves of this Truth. For ſuppoſe you were in a journey, and you ſhould be told of, nay ſhould ſee, a great Pit or Precipice, to which, and no whither elſe, that Road did directly lead; would you think of any other means to avoid it, but only by turning into another path? Though you ſhould quiver and tremble like a Leaf when it is ſhaken with the Wind;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59159:9"/>though you ſhould conceive the greateſt horrour, and offer never ſo many Prayers and Vows; nay though you turned your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about, and looked the contrary way; yet if ſtill you ſhould proceed and go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in that Road, you would moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurle your ſelves (though you turn'd your backs of it, and were loth to ſee it) into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable ruine. This is exactly the caſe of every Sinner; who, beſides that his way is uneaſie and rugged, putting him to a great deal of pain, and coſting him may a fall, hath the Pit of Hell, a bottomleſs Pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which burns with Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſet evidently before his eyes: Nay, is manifeſtly deſtroying his Body, his Eſtate, his Reputation; and which is more, is link'd in a wicked ſociety with thoſe, that by their riot and luxury, prophaneneſs and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, neglect of all things but their ſottiſh pleaſures, are bringing the Countrey where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they live to utter ruine; putting, as I may ſay, an ancient Kingdom and famous Church into moſt lamentable confuſion; in the midſt of which they are all like to periſh. It is a fooliſh thing for any of them to imagine they can avoid it, becauſe perhaps they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59159:10"/>ſometimes dread it, and ſhiver at the thoughts of it; becauſe they cry to Heaven when they ſee the danger, to deliver them from it; or at every ſtep, ſuppoſe, fall down on their faces, and humble themſelves, beſeeching God to reſcue them from this ruine: nay, put on Sackcloth (though alas! who is there now that is ſo religious?) and roll themſelves in duſt and aſhes. If when they get up again, they ſtill go on, and will not forſake their evil way, Heaven it ſelf cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from deſtruction, having appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that fearful end for ſuch obſtinate, refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Sinners; who will not be ſaved, unleſs he make the Fire not to burn, and the Sea not to drown: that is, alter the very nature of things, for the ſake of thoſe that deſerve ſo ill of him.</p>
            <p>Hoping therefore that, every one of you being convinced of this, the repreſentation of the danger of impenitency will, at leaſt, move you to deſign and begin a change of your lives, I ſhall treat of that at this time; which is the <hi>ſecond</hi> part of my Text: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Bleſſed Lord threatens, that unleſs the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> repented, he would <hi>come quickly to her, and fight againſt them with the ſword of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59159:10"/>
Which words contain in them theſe IV. Conſiderations, to ſtir us up to repentance.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Firſt,</hi> That if men do not amend their lives, eſpecially after many warnings, clear convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and a change wrought in their minds and judgments, it turns the greateſt kindneſs of God into anger and diſpleaſure.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. That</hi> it wearies the very patience and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering of God: <hi>to which we are more indebted than we imagine; and ſhould it forſake us, our condition is left very woful.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> To ſuch perſons the moſt gracious God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an enemy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV. And accordingly</hi> they muſt expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the execution of all his threatnings againſt them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>How all theſe ariſe out of the words, will appear in the handling of them.</p>
            <div n="1" type="consideration">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſay, That not to amend after God hath often called and perſwaded us to it, nay convinced us of the neceſſity of it, turns his greateſt kindneſs into anger and diſpleaſure. If there be no change wrought in your lives,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59159:11"/>you ſhall find a ſad change in his proceedings, and the methods of his Providence towards you. This I gather from that Phraſe, <hi>I will come unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come unto thee?</hi> What better News can there be than this (would one think) if he read no further? What more welcome Gueſt can we have than God himſelf? who is wont in theſe terms to expreſs his tender love and kindneſs towards Sinners. This is the thing that we pray for and entreat, That the Lord would be pleaſed to be ſo gracious as to <hi>come</hi> to our ſouls. And it is very true; this is the firſt ſignification of the Phraſe, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his Grace and favour, whereby he is moved to begin a kind Treaty with us: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto us and beſeeching us that he may have our affections; and that we will not diſpoſe of them to any one elſe but him, that loves us with ſo much tenderneſs.</p>
               <p>But then behold! what obſtinate impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency doth. It puts a ſtop to theſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and turns the courſe of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence another way. It changes all this love and good will, into anger, diſpleaſure and jealouſie. His <hi>coming</hi> now ſignifies quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing; His appearing is dreadful;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59159:11"/>His preſence is frightful, and aſtoniſhing: for He comes on another buſineſs; not to bleſs, but to curſe; not to beſtow favours, but to puniſh and execute vengeance.</p>
               <p>There is a double <hi>coming</hi> of God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: One with Offers and Tenders of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; the other with a Rod in his hand to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe our contempt and abuſe of the mercy offered. They that will not receive him in the former way, ſhall be forced to receive him in the latter. Though they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and reject his Grace; they ſhall not be able to defend themſelves from the effects of his heavy diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>The very name of our Bleſſed Saviour, if you obſerve it, was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>He that cometh,</hi> xi. <hi>Matt.</hi> 3. And what did he <hi>come</hi> for? He himſelf tells you what his firſt buſineſs was, x. <hi>John</hi> 10. <hi>I am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly.</hi> But when (as he complains) men <hi>would not come unto him, that they might have life,</hi> v. <hi>John</hi> 40. when <hi>He came unto his own, and his own received him not,</hi> i. <hi>John</hi> 11. Then you hear of another ſadder <hi>coming</hi> of his, i. <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. <hi>Behold, he cometh with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they that ſhut their eyes before, and in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59159:12"/>their blind rage <hi>pierced him,</hi> and wounded him to death as a Malefactor) <hi>and all the kindreds of the earth ſhall wail becauſe of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>coming</hi> at the firſt is to invite us to come unto him, xi. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. where you may read how he expects that all thoſe Souls which groan under their ſins, and complain of the heavy load of them, all thoſe who ſigh that they have committed them, ſhould be weary of them and throw off the burthen; take another courſe, and come to ſubmit themſelves to the yoke of his holy Laws. But if they will not be perſwaded to this, all their entreaties will never perſwade him to ſave them. His heart will be turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and He would have us mark how much he is diſpleaſed at them, what a change and wonderful alteration there is in his deſign upon them. For <hi>Behold the Lord cometh with ten thouſands of his holy ones, to execute Judgment upon all, and to convince all that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly among them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches, which ungodly Sinners have ſpoken againſt him,</hi> Jude 14, 15.</p>
               <p>And thus the word <hi>viſit</hi> in Scripture is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently uſed: Sometimes for Gods bringing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59159:12"/>his bleſſings to thoſe, to whom he is ſaid to come; and ſometimes for his laying his ſtripes on the back of thoſe Fools, that were inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his love. I need not name the places, ſome of which I alledged the laſt Day of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and Prayer: And I make mention of all this only to this purpoſe, That you may ſee what the effect of impenitency is. If you will not change, God will. Not himſelf indeed, for He was always thus reſolved, but his dealings with you: which you ſhall not find ſo favourable to you as they have been. He will not always wait to be ſo gracious as he is at preſent; for He is not inſenſible of all the affronts, that impudent Sinners put upon Him. He will take another courſe, ſince they will not; and meet them, as you ſhall hear preſently, after another manner than he was wont to do: making them know what it is to abuſe the goodneſs of their gracious God.</p>
               <p>You would have him indeed, to change his Laws for your ſakes; nay to change Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and go back with his Word: to love thoſe ſins which he cannot but hate, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that, which he hath told you he will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: a change which is impoſſible to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59159:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59159:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59159:14"/>made. But another change, every man that goes on ſtill in his treſpaſſes, ſhall find to his coſt: a change which he would by no means ſuffer, but which God hath purpoſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed and will not repent; which is, that He will not always ſtrive with men in ſo much love, but make Himſelf known to them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, in tokens of his anger and wrath.</p>
               <p>And that now would lead me to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> thing: only before we leave this, let us a little ſeriouſly conſider it. Have you ſo much reaſon to love your ſins, that rather than change your lives, you care not though God turn his loving kindneſs into diſpleaſure? After your ſins have turned the World up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down, and made it ſuch a confuſed and uncomfortable place as we now find it, do you not care though they reach up unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and make ſtill a greater alteration there, to our utter deſtruction? Is it of no concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in what manner God comes to viſit you? Is it all one whether he clothe himſelf with wrath and put on vengeance, or come as a Friend, and make affectionate addreſſes to your Souls? Would you have Him that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to knock at the door of your hearts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59159:14"/>to come in, and entertain you with fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival joys; break in upon you with a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful violence, and fill you with the terrours of the Lord, with an amazed Conſcience, with benumming fears, with ghaſtly apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the wrath to come, with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Hell fire; and that not to turn but to torment you?</p>
               <p>Or can you be content that He ſhould come againſt this ſinful Nation, <hi>to break down what He hath built up, and to pluck up that which he hath planted,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaks of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, xlv. 4.? Or would it be as welcome a ſound as any other to hear ſuch a Cry as that in the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> ii. 1. <hi>The day of the Lord cometh, it is nigh at hand, a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, a day of clouds and of thick darkneſs?</hi> wherein he will come to laſh us with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt ſcourge of all other, for the abuſe of the light of his glorious Goſpel, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſal of his Meſſengers, and our ſlighting all his benefits, and continuing incorrigible under his Judgments.</p>
               <p>O do not preſume that you ſhall never ſee ſuch a diſmal time, becauſe he hath not yet made you ſo miſerable. Do not put away far from you this evil day; nor imagine you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59159:15"/>ſhall always hear nothing but his kind invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and his loving entreaties, his good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and his gracious promiſes: if you will not be perſwaded by them to turn unto Him, He will turn away from you and ſet himſelf againſt you; He will not always ſtrive in vain with you, but reſolve at laſt (though much againſt his firſt deſign) to abandon ſuch ſtiffnecked Sinners, and pronounce ſuch a Sentence on them as that in the Prophet, i. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai.</hi> 24. <hi>Ah, I will eaſe me of mine Adverſaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies.</hi> And that is the next Conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="consideration">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>A continued courſe of ſin, doth in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion weary the patience and tire the long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of our moſt merciful and indulgent Lord and Maſter. For He ſays here in my Text, <hi>I will come unto thee QUICKLY.</hi> There is a time when he will bear no longer, but bring the Controverſie to a ſpeedy iſſue; in the ruine and deſtruction of thoſe that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him.</p>
               <p>Now though there are many ſigns menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in Scripture of an approaching ruine, yet I ſhall name but <hi>two.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is, When
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59159:15"/>Men have been not only often rebuked for their ſins, but convinced of their guilt and danger, and have had their hearts ſet againſt them, and yet will not amend. For which we have the known Maxim of the Wiſe Man, xxix. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. <hi>He that being often reproved, hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</hi> This is a mortal mark upon that perſon: A token of a plague of the heart ſo incurable, that nothing is to be expected but a ſudden death. Which will ſeize on ſuch men, if not preſently, yet on a ſudden, as to them; in a moment, when they look not for it; but think themſelves in peace and ſafety. Thus it was in the days of <hi>Noah;</hi> and thus it was at our <hi>Saviours</hi> coming to deſtroy his Crucifiers; and thus we ſee it oftimes with our eyes, or hear of it with our ears, that the confident and the merry Sinner is in an inſtant cut off, and goes down into the Pit.</p>
               <p>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> The condition of impenitent perſons is never more dangerous, than when they remain unreformed, after many puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have been inflicted on them, by divers ſtrokes of the Rod of God. Which ſeems to be ſuppoſed in thoſe words of our Saviour, in his Letter to the laſt of theſe Churches, iii. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. <hi>As many as I love, I rebuke and chaſten: be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59159:16"/>zealous therefore and repent.</hi> As if he had ſaid, When I would do good to mens ſouls, as long as I have any hope of them, I correct and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them; that I may reduce them to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. It concerns you therefore highly to ſtir up your ſelves to repent in good earneſt of thoſe ſins, for which you have ſmarted much alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: for there are no means to be uſed after theſe, but you muſt periſh, if they do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon your hearts. And this reaſon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> gives of the utter deſolation which was coming upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ix. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>For the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple turneth not unto him that ſmiteth them, neither do they ſeek the Lord of hoſts. Therefore the Lord will cut off from Iſrael head and tail, branch and ruſh in one day.</hi> To which many places might be added out of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> but one ſhall ſuffice, vii. <hi>Jer.</hi> 27, 28. <hi>Therefore thou ſhalt ſpeak theſe words unto them, but they will not hearken to thee: thou ſhalt alſo call upon them, but they will not anſwer thee. But thou ſhalt ſay unto them, This is a Nation that obeyeth not the voice of the Lord their God, nor receiveth correction: truth is periſhed, and is cut off from their mouth.</hi> That is to ſay, It is to no purpoſe to ſpeak to them any more. Thou mayeſt preach and beſtow thy labour upon them; but there will be no fruit of it. And therefore all that I have further to command
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59159:16"/>thee, is to pronounce this Judgment upon them; that they are a people, who will not be moved to their duty, either by my word, or by my correction; and therefore I give them over, as having no hope they will ever be reclaimed. <hi>Cut off thy hair, O Jeruſalem</hi> (in token of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is,) <hi>and caſt it away, and take up a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on high places; for the Lord hath rejected and forſaken the generation of his wrath.</hi> So it follows there, ver. 29. to the terrour of future Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who ſhould read this doleful Sentence upon thoſe who had once been very dear to God; but were now, by reaſon of their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wickedneſs, become good for nothing but to be made examples to all poſterity, of his ſoreſt diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>And now, my Brethren, what do you think, when you bring theſe things nearer home? Are neither of theſe ſigns and tokens of ſpeedy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to be found upon the Sinners of this Nation? Or rather do we not ſee both theſe marks of our Lords coming quickly to reckon with us, for our abuſe of his long patience and forbearance of us? Have you not been often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and felt the light of God pierce into your very hearts? Hath He not made you ſee the evil of your ways; and ſo powerfully bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enclined your wills towards Him, as to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59159:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59159:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59159:18"/>make you reſolve to become better men? Hath he not alſo humbled this Nation by his mighty hand; and ſent more Plagues than one to call us to repentance? Firſt, He made us ſigh and groan under the miſeries of a war; and then under thoſe of a ſore Peſtilence, which quickly, and as in a moment, ſmote down thouſands of us, and laid them in their Graves. After which a dreadful Fire quickly followed, which was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with that moſt diſgraceful attempt, which our Enemies made upon our Ships, the Bulwarks of this Land: and with many calamities ſince of another ſort, which have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt diſſolved the Bonds of Society; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that mutual confidence which ought to be between our Prince and his people; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered our Religion and Liberties; and brought us into ſuch a condition, that we ſcarce know which way to extricate our ſelves out of thoſe perplexities, in which our ſins have intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us.</p>
               <p>What ſhould every one of us then do, who ſtill ſurvive the War, the Plague, and all the reſt of Gods Judgments, but ſpeed our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment of life? You may think, perhaps, that the danger is now over, after ſo many puniſhments: but in truth there is greater danger than ever, if you ſtill go on to provoke
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59159:18"/>the Lord to jealouſie. For what ſhould He do with a people, but caſt them off, who will not be turned, no not by ſuch a mighty hand and outſtretched arm, from their wicked courſes? What our Saviour ſaith concerning thoſe whom <hi>Pilate</hi> ſlew together with their Sacrifices, and on whom the Tower in <hi>Siloam</hi> fell, [<hi>Suppoſe ye, that thoſe Galilaeans were Sinners above all the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilaeans, becauſe they ſuffered ſuch things; or thoſe eighteen the greateſt Sinners in Jeruſalem, becauſe the Tower fell on them, and killed them,</hi> &amp;c. xiii. <hi>Luke</hi> 1, 2, 3.] the ſame may I ſay to you with a ſmall alteration: Think you that thoſe men who were ſlain in the late wars, were Sinners above all the people of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they were cut off, and left you alive? <hi>I tell you nay, but except ye repent, ye ſhall alſo periſh.</hi> Or thoſe eighty or ninety thouſand that fell by the Plague, think you that they were Sinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all men that dwelt in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter? I tell you nay; but except ye repent, ye ſhall alſo periſh.</hi> The time will come, when you ſhall alſo be called to an account for your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency; if you ſtill go on in it: and who knows how near that time may be? In all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, it will come the more ſpeedily, if we take no warning neither by Gods Word, nor by his Rod. Therefore I beſeech you quickly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59159:19"/>before it be too late, to hearken to that voice, which ſaith, <hi>Return, return, O ye backſliding Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> If ever you mean to return, return now unto me, ſaith the Lord: and if you will put away your abominations out of my ſight, then ſhall you be ſettled in peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity.</p>
               <p>Conſider that Parable which St. <hi>Luke</hi> there adds, and read a deſcription of your own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8. You are a people planted as in a Garden of God; whoſe Goſpel is not only come to you, but hath ſtayed long with you. He hath taken great care of you; and hath dreſſed and pruned you, that you might bring forth the fruit, which the knowledge of Chriſt ought to produce. Many ſhowers of his Grace have fallen upon you; and you have long felt the warm beams of the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, to make you fruitful. And therefore, think alſo with your ſelves, that He hath come many years <hi>ſeeking fruit;</hi> and expecting to ſee ſome good grow out of all this care and coſt of his love. But alas! what hath He found when He came to viſit you? May He not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, as He doth there, <hi>I have come theſe three years</hi> (or rather, <hi>one three year after another, many times told over</hi>) <hi>ſeeking fruit, and find none?</hi> Is it not a wonder then that He hath not pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59159:19"/>the Sentence upon us, which there follows; <hi>Cut them down, why cumber they the ground?</hi> Is it not the greater wonder, ſeeing ſo many others have had this heavy doom paſſed upon them? O admire at the patient and long-ſuffering kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, which hath interpoſed on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and moved Him to <hi>let you alone</hi> both <hi>that</hi> year, and <hi>this</hi> year alſo. Firſt, In <hi>that</hi> year; I mean that fatal year of cutting down, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out of the Vineyard: when ſo many thouſands periſhed in the late dreadful mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And now I may adde in <hi>this</hi> year alſo, this remarkable year; when the Axe was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, laid to the root of the Tree: Our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I mean, had laid a deep Deſign, ſtrongly grounded, and cloſely carried on, to cut us off and deſtroy both root and branch; and, for any thing we know, in one day. For that <hi>there now is, and hath been for divers years laſt paſt, a horrid and treaſonable Plot and Conspiracy, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and carried on by thoſe of the Popiſh Religion, for the murthering of his Majeſties Sacred Perſon, and for ſubverting the Proteſtant Religion, and the ancient and eſtabliſhed Government of this Kingdom;</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come now, in effect, the ſenſe of the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled having declared, in a Reſolve of theirs, <hi>nemine contradicente</hi> (upon <hi>March</hi> 25. laſt paſt)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59159:20"/>that they are fully ſatisfied, by the proofs they have heard, of the truth of it.</p>
               <p>And conſidering their induſtrious endeavours to conceal it, even now that it is diſcovered, (whereas in reaſon, they ſhould be the moſt zealous of all other men, were they innocent, to have it thoroughly examined) their ſtrong Confederacies and ſtedfaſt Combinations, their many Oaths of ſecrecy, and obſtinate reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtick to the Deſign and to each other; it is a wonder that it hath not been effected, and that ſudden deſtruction hath not come upon us, as pain upon a Woman in travail.</p>
               <p>But let us not content our ſelves merely with admiration of his amazing Providence over us, which hath prolonged a while (we know not for how long or ſhort a time) the ſeaſon of Grace unto us; let us not preſume to abuſe this patience (for ſo we are to eſteem it, not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect deliverance) nor be ſo fooliſh as to imagine that it will laſt always: but think with our ſelves rather, that <hi>the Lord of the Vineyard</hi> may, it is poſſible, have reſolved, after <hi>this</hi> year, or in ſome ſhort ſpace, after this new Husbandry of his, and ſuch extraordinary pains and care to ſave us, that we ſhall be cut down indeed, if we will not bring forth fruit worthy of the Goſpel. And therefore, looking upon this as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59159:20"/>the day, wherein you may know and improve the things belonging to your peace, <hi>be zealous,</hi> as our Lord exhorts, <hi>and repent:</hi> be quick and ſpeedy, active and diligent in this weighty bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, now in this your day, leſt you never have ſuch an opportunity again, but miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly periſh in your ſins.</p>
               <p>Conſider, I beſeech you; do you not pray to God continually (if you have any ſenſe of Religion) that He would quickly diſſipate all our fears; by laying more and more open, and then utterly defeating all the wicked contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our enemies againſt us? Do you not think that He ſtays very long, before He bring to light the very bottom of the Plot; and make their Treaſons ſo viſible to all the World, that none may be able to gainſay it? Do you not think there is reaſon to tremble (when you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly reflect upon it) to ſee in what a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, unſettled and naked condition we are; in danger to be over-run with Foreign Enemies, ſhould they make an attempt upon us? Are you not all therefore ready to ſay, <hi>Lord, make haſt to help us! make no tarrying, O our God!</hi> O my Beloved, ſay the ſame to your ſelves; for there is the ſtop. Labour and prevail with your own Souls, that they would make haſte, that they would make no tarrying: but inſtantly turn to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59159:21"/>God, in works meet for repentance; that ſo both his preſent Judgments may be removed, and worſe prevented.</p>
               <p>I know nothing that can hinder the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this reaſonable motion, unleſs it be this, That men ſee there is not always ſuch a ſpeedy courſe taken with Sinners, and therefore they preſume God will ſtill bear with them. For they themſelves have lived and ſinned many years, and have eſcaped many dangers: and though they have been affrighted ſometimes with ſuch Sermons as this, yet they were worſe ſcared than hurt. Still all things are as they were; they are very well and proſperous, they have all that their hearts deſire: and therefore there hearts grow hard, and they ſuppoſe they are in no ſudden danger.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this, I ſhall ſay nothing but what is contained in the <hi>Third</hi> Conſideration here in my Text; which is,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="consideration">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>That all impenitent perſons, as they oppoſe God ſo they, have God for their Enemy: and He will ſet himſelf in oppoſition to them. For He tells this Church, That if they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, He will <hi>fight againſt them.</hi> Which denotes, that He would become their Adverſary, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59159:21"/>look upon them as Rebels, nay as irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Enemies: who will never ſubmit to His Divine Government; which is concerned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to deſtroy them. So that theſe impenitent Wretches, who go on reſolvedly in their ſins, notwithſtanding all that He can do to reclaim them, gain but little by the patience and lenity of God towards them; and it is but a ſmall comfort that He doth not preſently ſtrike them: ſeeing it is certain, as the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it, that He <hi>is bending his Bow, whetting his Sword, and preparing for them the inſtruments of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this I need not ſay much, nor will the time permit it. It is ſufficient to know, That ſometimes the deferring of Execution is a piece of hoſtility; and makes the blow heavier when it comes. They are but treaſuring and heaping up to themſelves wrath, againſt the day of wrath, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, ii. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4, 5.) who will not be led by the goodneſs of God, no, nor His Judgments to repentance; but proceed to adde ſin to ſin, till a moſt terrible vengeance break out upon them. Which may be deferred perhaps from time to time, but with no other deſign than a great Prince hath, who is ſo powerful that He can have the better of his Enemies when he will; and therefore forbears to fall upon them not becauſe he means to ſpare
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59159:22"/>them, but only becauſe he waits for an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, when he may do the more terrible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and take the ſevereſt revenge on thoſe whom he intends to ruine. What do ſinful men mean then <hi>to provoke the Lord to jealouſie? Are they ſtronger than He?</hi> Will you not fear Him, becauſe He doth not inſtantly ſmite? Shall your hearts be ſet in you to do evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Judgment is not always ſpeedily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt an evil work? Will you dare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Him, as if He could not, or preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Him, as if He would not puniſh? Let me tell you, He is the more to be feared and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if you underſtood your ſelves, for this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance. He delays to ſtrike, not becauſe He cannot; but becauſe He can when He pleaſes: not becauſe He will not; but becauſe He will do it at ſuch a time, when it will moſt ſerve the Wiſdom of His Providence. We are ignorant of all the reaſons, why God doth not do with all, as He doth with ſome. We know not for what cauſes they are, that He doth not come ſo quickly to reckon with one wicked man, as with another. It is enough to affright us out of our wicked ways, to know that He looks upon ſuch perſons as His Enemies; and that He will take the fitteſt ſeaſon to come <hi>and wound the head of his Enemies, the ſcalp of him that goeth on ſtill in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59159:22"/>his treſpaſſes.</hi> For that is the laſt Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="consideration">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>That ſuch perſons as will not repent, being ſo often admoniſhed, ſo patiently born withal, ſo lovingly chaſtiſed and corrected; muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but the execution of all our Lords threatnings againſt obſtinate Sinners. So He ſaith, <hi>I will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth.</hi> For the underſtanding of which Phraſe, you muſt look back to the firſt Chapter of this Book, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. where Chriſt is repreſented as having a <hi>ſharp ſword,</hi> and that <hi>two-edged, going out of his mouth.</hi> The mouth it not the proper place for a ſword to be in, which uſes to be girded to the thigh, or, when it is unſheathed, to be taken into the hand. By this Phraſe therefore is deſcribed the gracious method of our Lord Chriſt; who threatens before He ſtrikes. His ſword at firſt is only in his mouth; that is, He declares his vengeance which He will take againſt the rebellious; and makes Proclamation that He will come and deſtroy them, if they do not repent. But if theſe threatnings and denunciations of vengeance do not prevail; if, notwithſtanding all his declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they contemn His authority, and will
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59159:23"/>not ſtand in awe of Him as their Lord and their Judge: He will proceed to do as He hath ſaid, and <hi>fight againſt them,</hi> as He tells us here in my Text, with this ſword, which before He threatned ſhould come upon them to cut them off. Now no man <hi>fights</hi> with a ſword, but it is in his hand: and therefore theſe words can ſignifie nothing leſs, than that the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments He had threatned and ſolemnly denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſhould fall upon hardened Sinners; and that He would execute what He had reſolved and make good his word, if they took no heed to the warnings He had given them.</p>
               <p>Know then, all ye that go on fearleſly in your evil ways, notwithſtanding all that we can ſay from God unto you; that you ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hear the mere thunder of terrible words, the ſound and noiſe of wrath and damnation hereafter, of blood and war, of plagues and tumults and ſubverſions of Churches and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms here (that is, the ſword will not always be in his mouth) but you ſhall feel in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion the ſtrokes of his heavy diſpleaſure; and He will make you know by diſmal effects, that His words are not light and vain, which vaniſh into Air; but they remain in everlaſting force, and ſhall all be fulfilled.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Sword</hi> being <hi>two-edged,</hi> which cuts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59159:23"/>on both ſides, his fighting with it, may denote the execution of his threatnings both upon the Bodies and upon the Souls of his Enemies: whom He puniſhes oftimes in their outward, as well as in their ſpiritual eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="examination">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, Thoſe words are very terrible, which you meet withal in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Letter to the next Church, <hi>ver.</hi> 21, 22, 23. of this Chapter, <hi>I gave her ſpace to repent of her fornication, but ſhe repented not. Behold, I will caſt her into a Bed, and them that commit Adultery with her into great tribulation, except they repent of their deeds. And I will kill her Children with death, and all the Churches ſhall know that I am He which ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the reins and hearts, and I will give unto every one of you, according to your works.</hi> Which if we apply to our ſelves, we cannot deny but that we have been already <hi>in great tribulation;</hi> and what further puniſhments the righteous Lord hath reſerved for us, except we repent, we are not able certainly to tell: but this is ſure, that it is not likely there ſhould be any peace to ſuch a wicked people. Our ſins are ſo crying, that they will not ſuffer us to be quiet, but give us further diſturbance, till they have utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded us: unleſs we will part with theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59159:24"/>of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and become more obedient Chriſtians. There have been innumerable Sermons preached, and Books printed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate this truth, That all thoſe ſins which are now ſo rife among us, <hi>ſloth and negligence, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xury and exceſs, whoredom and adultery, perfidiouſneſs and diſhoneſty, infidelity or indifference in Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all Government Civil and Spiritual,</hi> &amp;c. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tend unto (and can end in nothing elſe but) the ſubverſion of thoſe Families, and that Kingdom and Church wherein they reign: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the Divine Juſtice is concerned to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, and will be avenged, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks, of ſuch a Nation as this. And who is there that doth not ſee, there are inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Divine Juſtice ready at hand, bloody inſtruments, that offer themſelves to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and are prepared to do the execution, if our repentance do not move Him, by ſome miraculous Providence, to prevent it? The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts I mean, the ſworn Enemies of our peace and ſettlement; who, as they want no will ſo, have behaved themſelves as if they thought they did not want power to deſtroy us. Men of as wicked principles, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of miſchief can invent: of no Faith, no Juſtice, no Charity, no Moderation (if they be ſpirited by them, who now rule in that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59159:24"/>Church) but inflamed with a falſe zeal for God and Religion; which will let them ſtick at no Cruelty, no Butchery, no Treachery or treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable attempt, to compaſs their deſired end. We may ſay of them as <hi>David</hi> doth of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, v. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. <hi>There is no faithfulneſs in their mouth, their inward part is very wickedneſs: their throat is an open Sepulchre, though they flatter with their tongue.</hi> And xxxviii. 19. <hi>Our enemies are lively, and ſtrong: they that hate us wrongfully, are many in number.</hi> So many, and ſo induſtrious and deſperately bent to ſeek our ruine, that <hi>if the Lord had not been on our ſide, they had ſwallowed us up quick; when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</hi> And we may be ſure it is not quenched, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more incenſed by this diſappointment: So that we had need, with ſerious repentance, earneſtly beſeech Him, in the words of <hi>David</hi> elſewhere, xvii. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13. <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them and caſt them down: deliver my ſoul from the wicked, which is a Sword of thine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which words teach us, That the wicked are one kind of <hi>Sword,</hi> which my Text may ſpeak of, wherewith the Lord fights againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners: whom He puniſhes very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by other Sinners like themſelves. And there is no ſort of puniſhment that doth ſuch dreadful execution, as the <hi>fierceneſs of man;</hi> if
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59159:25"/>the Lord do not reſtrain it. We have reaſon therefore to cry, in the words of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> (which we may apply to this buſineſs) <hi>O Sword of the Lord, how long will it be e're thou be quiet? Put up thy ſelf into thy Scabbard; reſt and be ſtill,</hi> xlvii. 6. Let us ſee no more wars, no more bloodſhed, no more ſheathing our Swords in one another Bowels. But then we muſt add, as it there follows, <hi>How can it be quiet, if the Lord have given it a charge againſt us; and if here He hath appointed it?</hi> If He reſolve this way to puniſh us, there is no way to eſcape it (but by repentance) and we cannot imagine how ſore a puniſhment it may prove: for <hi>the tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> xii. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.) <hi>are cruel.</hi> Which was never more verified of any ſort of wicked men, than of thoſe Jeſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Zealots, who are now inraged againſt us, <hi>and hate us,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, xxv. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>with cruel hatred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We cannot tell yet how they intended to have treated us now, but we know what they intended, and what they did in former times. Particularly in the Year 1588. when <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro de Valdez,</hi> a great Commander in the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Invaſion, confeſſed to the Lords of the Council (who examined him after he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, What meant thoſe Whips of Cord and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59159:25"/>Wire wherewith their Ships were ſtored) that <hi>they intended,</hi> if they had prevailed, <hi>to have whipt us Hereticks to death.</hi> This he anſwered in a bold manner; and being further asked what they would have done with our young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, replied as boldly, <hi>All above ſeven years old ſhould have gone the ſame way with their Fathers: the reſt ſhould have lived; only we would have branded them in the Forehead with the Letter</hi> L, <hi>ſignifying</hi> Lutheran; <hi>and reſerved them for perpetual bondage.</hi> This the Relator (D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sharp</hi>) takes God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he received from two of the greateſt Lords of the Council after his Examination: with a Commandment to publiſh it to the Queens Army which lay at <hi>Tilbury,</hi> in his next Sermon.</p>
               <p>It may be objected indeed that this was only an inſolent rant of one of thoſe huffing Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; who intended, as he profeſſed, not only to ſubdue our Nation, but to root it wholly out: and there cannot be, you may fanſie, any ſo barbarous among our ſelves, that deſign ſuch a total deſtruction of us they call Hereticks. To which I have nothing to ſay but this, That the ordinary Diſcourſe of Papiſts here in former times, hath been as bloody and cruel as can be imagined: and we have little reaſon to think they have leſs venome now, that they have more power by the encreaſe of their numbers.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59159:26"/>For I find theſe words in an Expoſition upon 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> ii. printed fifty years ago,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>John Squire,</hi> Serm. V. Page 138.</note> by a famous Preacher in the City of <hi>London, Know we not their common threatnings? What they whiſper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Common People, what they will do when their day doth come? (Chriſt grant that their day may never come.) When it ſhall come, do they not whiſper that they will no more hew down the branches, but tear up the very roots of the reformation, rooting out every Profeſſor thereof?</hi> Which agrees too plainly with what we read in a late Traitors Letters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their hopes now to extirpate that peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Hereſie (as they miſcal our holy Religion) which hath ſpread it ſelf through theſe Northern Parts of the World. Nor have their practices been unſuitable, as the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion</hi> alone ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently teſtifies; wherein three hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſouls were ſent to the other World, as not fit to live in this; for no other cauſe but their Religion: and it is manifeſt they then intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have left none remaining in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey but themſelves; if they could have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their blood-thirſty deſires.</p>
               <p>Which things I remember for no other end, but to awaken you to a ſerious repentance of thoſe ſins, which have brought us near the brink of the like deſtruction: leſt the Lord deliver
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59159:26"/>us, at laſt, into the hands of theſe Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Whoſe tyranny is ſo inſupportable, that ſhould they prevail, the Poſterity of them who now wiſh for that woful day, would ſadly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of it in future times; and curſe the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe who brought them into ſuch ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Let them but read the complaints and hearken to the groans of their Forefathers under the Roman bondage, before the Reformation of Religion; and they may be convinced of their folly, or madneſs rather, in deſiring and indeavouring to return unto it. All the World ſighed for deliverance from it, particularly <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> as we find in the publick Acts of thoſe Countries: who ſaid of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s tyranny, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did of the burthen of Jewiſh Ceremonies, that it was <hi>a yoke which neither they nor their Fathers were able to bear.</hi> 
                  <q>And among all the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Records</q> (to uſe the words of him that ſet out the <hi>Review of the Council of Trent</hi> in our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) <q>which there are of the Popes Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there are not to be found more woful Tragedies of his tyranny, than ſuch as were acted upon our Stage. No higher Trophees erected to his ambition, than here in <hi>England.</hi> No more rare examples of devout, abuſed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, than among us. Till extream ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59159:27"/>made us deſpair into courage and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; when the avarice and exactions of <hi>Rome</hi> having left us nothing elſe, at laſt rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed us of our patience.</q> All our Hiſtories are full of proofs of this; which may eaſe me of the labour of relating any of them: nor is this a place ſo proper for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="examination">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Let me paſs rather to the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing, and turn towards you the other edge of this <hi>Sword</hi> which my Text ſpeaks of: which is the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his threatnings againſt the ſouls of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent; and ſending upon them ſpiritual judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Which if we have any ſenſe and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt think are the moſt grievous of all other: And here I might repreſent to you, what a diſmal thing it would be, if you ſhould have your eyes put out once more; and be buried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the darkneſs of ignorance and Popiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; being robbed of your reaſon, and made to believe the groffeſt abſurdities: and having no liberty left to examine any thing, be forced to follow blindly, whitherſoever your blind Guides will lead you. For this is the leaſt you can expect, if our inveterate enemies prevail over us. Suppoſe they ſhould be ſo kind as not to kill us, nor torment us, nor ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59159:27"/>much as impriſon us; yet they will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe the greateſt ſeverity againſt our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and endeavour to deſtroy that, though they ſhould ſpare us. The holy Scriptures muſt be impriſoned; your underſtandings and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits inthralled; the Worſhip of God prophaned and corrupted, the Idolatry of the Maſs erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the very Doctrine of repentance poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and all other ways of ſerving God, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Superſtition, abſolutely prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</p>
               <p>We may ſuffer our ſelves to be abuſed, if we pleaſe, with fair words and plauſible ſpeeches, wherewith they deceive the hearts of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: but whatſoever they ſay, and petition for themſelves, when they are under Hatches; they are reſolved, when they have power, to give no toleration to any Religion but their own. Thus <hi>Ribadeneir a</hi> (the famous Writer of the life of <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Founder of the Jeſuits) labours to prove at large in his Book of a <hi>Chriſtian Prince;</hi> 
                  <q>That it is impoſſible for Catholicks to unite with Hereticks in a firm bond of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to agree to live together in a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, quiet Body of a Commonwealth</q> (which is worthy our notice and remembrance, and ſo are his Reaſons.) <q>For how can one carry a Serpent in his boſome, ſaith he, and not be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59159:28"/>ulcerated by his bitings? or touch Pitch, and not be defiled? <hi>&amp;c. Or are there more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and inbred enmities between the Wolves and the Lambs, than there ought to be between Catholicks and Hereticks?</hi> No, ſaith he, the Council of <hi>Toledo</hi> determines, That no King hereafter ſhould reign, but before he aſcended the Throne, he ſhould ſwear, among other things, that he would permit no man who was not a Catholick to live in his Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> And if this be not ſufficient to ſhew what theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would be at, (who now are the ruling men in that Church) I might cite others, who make it <hi>equally dangerous to have two Religions in a Kingdom, and to have a Wife and a Whore in one and the ſame Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes indeed they confeſs the iniquity of the times (as they ſpeak) may be ſuch, that a Prince of their Religion may be forced to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ours; and ſolemnly do it by compact and agreement. But then they ſay again, That he being compelled unwillingly to fall into a guilt, muſt not willingly fall into another, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming what he hath done, when he hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to break the agreement. And they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed ſeveral ways to free ſuch a Prince from his obligation, when he thinks fit to null what in words he ſeemed to eſtabliſh: but I ſhall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59159:28"/>not trouble you with them; nor ſhould I have ſaid any thing at all of this, had it not ſeemed to me neceſſary to inform you, That <hi>whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may ſeem to give you with one hand, they have devices artificially and cunningly to take away with the other.</hi> Whereby they juſtifie what Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Deza</hi> ſaid in a Sermon of his in praiſe of their Founder <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Who was <hi>the mighty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> he told them, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the x. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>who came down from Heaven clothed with a Cloud, and a Rainbow was upon his head, and his face was as the Sun,</hi> &amp;c. And enquiring why he was repreſented as <hi>clothed with a Cloud,</hi> makes this anſwer; that it ſignifies that <hi>he hides and conceals his generous and ſublime counſels and deſigns:</hi> and repreſents alſo the Government of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, <hi>which manifeſt their effects, but hide their rules and their modes or manner of acting.</hi> As of old, ſaith he, a Cloud covered the Tabernacle of the Lord, and the Glory of the Lord enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into it: ſo God who hath built this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle on Earth (he means the Society of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi>) hath with the ſame wiſdom ordained, for the preſerving the honour of ſo holy a thing, <hi>ut ejus gubernandi ratio adeo ſecreta eſſet,</hi> that the reaſon and manner of its Government ſhould be ſo ſecret, that no man ſhould be able to know it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59159:29"/>
Which I think you ſee verified to the full at this day. We feel the effects of their Counſels, but we ſee not the ſecret Springs by which they move. They are <hi>covered with a Cloud</hi> indeed, and caſt a miſt before peoples eyes, by a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of cunning diſtinctions, crafty evaſions, and ſecret reſervations: wherein they inſtruct their Proſelytes, that they may be able to do the moſt villainous things; and yet not be ſeen, but lye concealed from the eyes of the world, even when they are caught, and many eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are produced of their wickedneſs. <hi>O my Soul,</hi> will every one here be apt to ſay (with good old <hi>Jacob</hi>) <hi>come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſſembly, my Honour, be not thou united,</hi> xlix. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. But it is not enough to pray againſt their artifices; we muſt take a more effectual courſe, by true repentance, to engage the wiſdom of Heaven on our ſide, to defeat their moſt crafty and ſubtile contrivances. Elſe we may be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened and gulled out of our Religion, if by outward force they cannot prevail againſt us, and return in time to our old blind devotion: according to the obſervation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Stephen,</hi> that when the Iſraelites would not obey <hi>Moſes,</hi> then in their hearts they turned back again into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> and then God turned and gave them up to worſhip the Hoſt of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59159:29"/>
But ſuppoſe none of theſe things ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal us; but we ſhould keep our Religion: what ſhall we be the better for it, if we do not repent? Nay, how much the worſe ſhall we grow, by the abuſe of his abundant Grace, and ſo many remarkable deliverances from our Enemies, which we have received? There are other ſpiritual evils, that He hath threatned to inflict upon the impenitent; and are the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt wounds, the ſharpeſt puniſhments, that He can give with this <hi>Sword of his mouth.</hi> They are ſuch as theſe, <hi>the withdrawing of his Grace, the taking away his holy Spirit; and conſequently cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to move their hearts unto repentance; denying them the helps they have had, and putting no ſuch ſtops to them in their evil courſes, as ſometimes they have found: but removing thoſe things which might excite and ſtir them up to amendment; and on the contrary permitting ſuch as may confirm them in their contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, whereby they become hardened, and ſealed up unto condemnation; to be puniſhed with everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, to take vengeance on all thoſe that know not God, and obey not the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are ſad and diſmal things, which ſhould ſtir up every one of our drowſie hearts, to mark and obſerve and lay hold upon every
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59159:30"/>good motion of God's good Spirit in our hearts unto repentance: leſt it depart away from us, and by degrees leave us inſenſible, utterly inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the things belonging to our peace. Which, one would think, ſhould be ſo dear to us (though we look no further than this preſent World) that we ſhould readily conſent to any thing that will procure it; and ſet our ſelves againſt that which obſtructs it, and will final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undo us. And that we all confeſs is our hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſins; For all the power of the Devil and of Men, though never ſo violently bent againſt us, cannot deſtroy us; unleſs we continue ſtill in the Plot, as I may call it, wherein we are engaged too deeply againſt our ſelves; by our wilful perſiſting in prophaneneſs, filthineſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Religion, and of that Authority which ſupports it; and ſuch like ſins: which have brought us into that low, that weak and contemptible condition; in which our enemies could never have hoped to have ſeen us, unleſs they had firſt debauched us.</p>
               <p>That hath been their great craft, as it was <hi>Balaam</hi>'s; to whoſe devices my Text hath a particular reſpect. He ſaw clearly there was no way to prevail againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but by enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them in <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Irreligion:</hi> and that there was no way to engage them in that, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59159:30"/>by inticing them to <hi>Fornication.</hi> So the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> excellently gloſs upon his Story<note n="*" place="margin">Apud Hotting. Smegma Orienta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, <hi>p. 444.</hi>
                  </note>: who introduce <hi>Balaam</hi> telling the Princes of <hi>Midian,</hi> That the holy Angels ſurrounded <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the King of Heaven and Earth was with them: ſo that neither Magick, nor any thing elſe, could prevail againſt them; unleſs they admitted ſome infidelity, or committed ſome grievous ſin. Then, ſaid he, the Creator will be angry with them, ſo that they ſhall periſh, and not one of them remain. For the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of which, he adviſed them to ſend the moſt beautiful Women in their Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, every one of them with the Idol which She worſhipped, in her hands: and that She ſhould offer her ſelf to be theirs, if they would eat of her Meat, drink of her Drink, and worſhip her God. This was <hi>eating things offered to Idols,</hi> mentioned before my Text; whereby many of them periſhed; and the reſt were ſaved, who ſeverely puniſhed theſe enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and thereby ſhewed their hatred and deteſtation of the wickedneſs of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
               <p>After which pattern Chriſt expected the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> ſhould be ſevere againſt all thoſe among them, who were ſeduced
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59159:31"/>from the Chriſtian purity in Doctrine and in Manners, by the like artifice of the Devils A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents. Whereby he knew he ſhould put them out of Chriſts favour; and if they continued in thoſe wicked courſes, quite unchurch them, and bring them again under his vaſſalage. This is the <hi>Repentance,</hi> which Chriſt here calls for in my Text: and which He requires of all Governours and thoſe in Authority Civil or Spiritual; that they ſhould not be ſlack in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſin, and ſuppreſſing all falſe Doctrine, and eſpecially thoſe leud opinions which lead men to all manner of looſneſs and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>For, if you obſerve it, the Church of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus</hi> had: been ſtedfaſt in the Faith in the time of perſecution, and when <hi>Antipas</hi> his faithful Martyr ſuffered, were a commendable people in many things (as we likewiſe in this Church, at leaſt our Forefathers, may be commended for this, that in the days of Fire and Faggot, many choſe to dye rather than to change their Religion.) But there were a <hi>few things</hi> which Chriſt had againſt them. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe they had thoſe among them, who <hi>held the Doctrine of Balaam,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe who <hi>held the Doctrine of the Nicolaitans:</hi> who were another ſort of filthy people; giving themſelves over
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59159:31"/>unto promiſcuous luſts of uncleanneſs. When He ſaith, <hi>They had ſuch among them,</hi> He means they connived at them, and did not eject them: For it was not their fault, that thoſe men held ſuch opinions; but that they ſuffered them without the cenſure of the Church. And then immediately He addes, <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come againſt thee quickly,</hi> &amp;c. As much as to ſay, You muſt ſuffer theſe men no longer among you; (that was their repentance, at that time) or if you do, I will not endure it; but will come and puniſh you for this indifference in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>Now I leave you all to judge, whether the Factors of the evil one, have not taken this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe to unchurch us; and we by our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence be not in the way to unchurch our ſelves. They have infuſed poyſonous princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples into mens minds, and taught them, for inſtance, to decry Marriage, as a fooliſh ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to think Fornication an innocent thing; and ſo to give up themſelves to commit all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs with greedineſs: that ſo, forgetting all reſpect to our Religion, they may in the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue make them Romaniſts, and proſelyte them to their Idolatrous Services; that is, make them ten times more the Children of the Devil, than they were befoee. And what other way
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59159:32"/>is there to be ſaved from the deſtruction which theſe and other vices will bring upon us, but (that which we are not willing to take) for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to repent of his own wickedneſs and turn to God: and then for thoſe who have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to ſet themſelves with all their might to puniſh and to root out ſuch wickedneſſes, with all the principles that lead unto them, together with the Abettors and Supporters of them?</p>
               <p>And here it may be fit to obſerve, That a <hi>few things,</hi> if very deſtructive to Religion, may provoke the Divine ſeverity againſt a Church. For they were no more, that Chriſt charges this Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> withal; and yet, if they did not amend, He threatens <hi>to come and fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them with the Sword of his mouth:</hi> What will become of us then, whom He hath ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to charge withal; if we go on ſtill to provoke Him with them to jealouſie? I doubt we cannot clear our ſelves from ſuch filthineſſes, as are here mentioned; nor from foul Doctines leading to them, which too many have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; nor from coldneſs and indifference in Religion, if not plain infidelity; nor from a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of heart in ſome to turn back to <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> again; nor from conniving at the defection which ſo many have made from Chriſts true Religion here eſtabliſhed, and not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59159:32"/>endeavouring to ſuppreſs all thoſe that ſeek to deſtroy it. And which is ſtill more, we are foully guilty of ſlighting that Authority, which ſhould call men to an account for all their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; and not only reprove and rebuke, but cenſure and chaſtiſe, and exerciſe Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline upon notorious Offenders. This is a thing not only laugh'd at and deſpiſed; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſcorned: nay, the Miniſters of Chriſt themſelves are but lightly eſteemed. For which, if there were nothing elſe, we may be ſure Chriſt will reckon with us.</p>
               <p>Reckon with us, did I ſay? He hath done it in part already; and yet we are not cured of this malignant humour: which makes me fear the ſaddeſt part of the reckoning is ſtill behind. Take the Prognoſtication in the words of a great Doctor of this Church<note n="*" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Jackson</hi> on the Creed, Book II. Chap. 9.</note>: who thus denounced God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt this Nation, a good while before the late Wars, upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, That he ſaw the people running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into this great ſin; which is marvellouſly encreaſed ſince that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtionleſs,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this open, malapert, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing diſobedience, to all Eccleſiaſtical Power, now open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed by the meaneſt, and countenanced by many great ones of the Laity, is the ſin which (to all that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59159:33"/>know Gods Judgments, or have been obſervant to look into the days of our viſitation) cries loudeſt in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties ears (more loud by much than the Prayers of Friars, Monks and Jeſuits do) for Gods vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this land. For vengeance to be executed by no other than our ſword, inveterate, malicious enemies; by no other grievances, than by the doubled grievances of the long-enraged Romaniſts iron-yoke: which is now prepared for us, ten times more heavy and irkſome than that was, which our Forefathers have born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray God this do not prove a true Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. If it do, we cannot ſay but we were forewarned; and that Gods Watchmen diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves, and told us beforehand of the danger. Which we had better prevent, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming more obedient to their godly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions; by ſubmitting to their juſt cenſures; by eſteeming them very highly for their works ſake; and giving them all due encouragement to do their duties ſincerely. And though ſome be negligent, and idle, or ignorant, let not either the baſeneſs or the leudneſs of any of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, tempt you to deſpiſe their office: For that's the reaſon (in that Doctors opinion) why God ſends no better men in many places. <hi>God knows,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for whoſe fake it is; but we may at fear it is eſpecially for the infidelity and diſloyalty of this people towards Him, and for their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59159:33"/>to his Meſſengers; that He ſends them ſuch idle, fooliſh and lewd Pastors, as they have in many places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Laity of this Land are ſo prone and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong to cast off Chriſts yoke, and to deny due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his faithful Miniſters; He therefore ſets ſuch Watchmen over them in many places, as they ſhall have no luſt to obey, in any thing that they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to them; but harden their hearts in infidelity and diſobedience.</hi> Which, I have ſhewn you already, is one of the moſt fearful Judgments, that God can inflict upon us; and which we ought to dread, more than the <hi>enraged Romaniſts iron-yoke;</hi> which, he ſaith, <hi>is prepared for us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been <hi>preparing</hi> many years; and it ſeems now to have been very near to be clapt, when we thought not of it, upon our necks. It is a Miracle of Gods mercy that it was not: But let not that make us too confident, that it ſhall never be laid upon us; nor fanſie it is quite broken in pieces, becauſe we are ſlipt from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it at preſent. For if our ſhameful diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel, and contempt of its Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſtill continue, (notwithſtanding that they are acknowledged to be much better now in moſt places, than when that Doctor wrote) I fear we do but feed our ſelves with vain hopes of an abſolute deliverance. Or ſuppoſe He
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59159:34"/>will not let them be the Inſtruments of that puniſhment, which our ſins deſerve (becauſe they of that Church are ſo exceeding wicked; ſo void, that is, of all faith, truth and honeſty; ſo perfidious, malicious and cruel: and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a colour and pretence of Religion; which warrants all theſe things, and makes them the more abominable) yet aſſure your ſelves He will find ſome other way, to execute the Judgments He hath threatned to the impenitent. There is ſome likelihood He will take them in their own craftineſs: but let not the hope of that tempt you to be ſecure; for He will deſtroy us too, in our impudent diſobedience, and hardneſs of heart; which will not be moved by any thing to come to repentance: No, not when we our ſelves acknowledge that we expect mercy and deliverance from Him, upon no other terms. For ſo we conſtantly pray, in the <hi>Collect for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from our enemies:</hi> where we firſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that to Him <hi>it juſtly belongs to puniſh Sinners, and to be merciful to them that truly repent:</hi> and then deſire Him to <hi>deliver us from the hand of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; to abate their pride, aſſwage their malice, and confound their devices.</hi> Unleſs we repent, we here confeſs that we have no reaſon to expect his ſalvation; but rather ſuch puniſhments, as He juſtly inflicts upon ſuch Sinners, as will notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59159:34"/>go on ſtill in thoſe treſpaſſes, whereby they ſee, they are in danger to periſh inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
               <p>Let me once more therefore beſeech you, as you love your ſouls, as you love your Religion, your Lives, your Liberties, and all that is dear to you; examine and ſearch and try your ſelves by the infallible teſt of God's moſt holy Word: lay your hearts to that Rule while you have it; and reſolve by God's gracious aſſiſtance, to bring them to a ſincere conformity with it.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially let all good men (whatſoever the reſt are pleaſed to do) apply their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to purifie themſelves more perfectly, to walk more circumſpectly, to ſhine as lights in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation; and to cry mightily unto God for his ſparing mercy. It is poſſible they may be ſaved, though He puniſh others. Nay, by their importunate cries unto Him, and ſollicitous prayers, day and night, for this poor Church and Kingdom, they may obtain ſome reſpite of his Judgments, and prevail for the putting them off till a further time: if they cannot quite avert them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ahab</hi>'s humiliation, you know, procured this favour: And therefore if all, both King and people, did this day imitate him, ſo far as with great ſorrow and affliction of Spirit to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59159:35"/>their offences, earneſtly beg pardon, cry for mercy with ſtrong and conſtant importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and reform ſome notorious ſins (though not all of which we are guilty) it might prove a prolonging of our tranquillity. Nay, it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as I ſaid, that, though others continue ſtill inſenſible and negligent yet, if all good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would make it their buſineſs every day to grow better, and to pray to God inceſſantly, that He would at leaſt forbear us, and have pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with us, expecting ſtill longer, if we will bring forth fruit worthy of his Goſpel; it is likely they might obtain this mercy, of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth and peace in our days.</p>
               <p>Let me ſpeak to you therefore in the words of a pious and learned man, before the late wars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All ye that fear God, and tremble under the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his wrath, give Him no reſt, ſtand up in the breach, make a ſtrong aſſault, as I may ſay, upon Heaven with your Prayers; give not over till you have received a gracious anſwer: till the ſins of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be pardoned, his imminent Judgments averted, his antient favours recovered; till He have rebuked Satan, and trodden Him under our feet; till He have fruſtrated the bloody hopes and deſires of the enemies of his Truth; till He build up the breaches, raiſe the ruines, and bind up the wounds of his Sion: Saying with Daniel, O Lord God, we have ſinned and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59159:35"/>iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet compaſſion and forgiveneſs is with Thee, O Lord: and therefore we beſeech Thee, hear the Prayers of thy Servants, and their Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and cauſe thy face to ſhine upon this Church, for thy Names ſake. O Lord, hear; O Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give; O Lord conſider, and do it: defer not, for thy own ſake, O our God: for thy Name is called upon us, and we are thy people.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59159:36"/>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59159:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED On the Late FAST, DECEM. xxii. 1680. Afternoon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rev. <hi>III. beginning of the</hi> third <hi>Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Remember therefore how thou haſt received and heard, and hold faſt, and repent.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE <hi>ſad and calamitous condition</hi> of this, once moſt happy, Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is ſo great and ſo viſible, that it can be no longer diſſembled: but we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (in the firſt Leſſon for this Morning Prayer, i. 5.) that <hi>the whole head is ſick, and the whole heart faint,</hi> &amp;c. which hath moved his Majeſty (by the deſire of his Parliament) to cauſe it to be proclaimed to all his people; that we may be awakened to look about us, and ſee how we may prevent
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59159:37"/>
               <hi>the dreadful Judgments which are now impending over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which hath occaſioned this deplorable ſtate of things is (as we are told in the <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> which called us hither) <hi>the impious and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Conſpiracies of a Popiſh Party; who have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plotted and intended the deſtruction of our Sovereign, the ſubverſion of the Government and Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed among us; but ſtill obſtinately proſecute their intentions, notwithſtanding Gods moſt wonderful diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their wickedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And one of the ways whereby they carry on this deſign, being (as we are there alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) <hi>by fomenting diviſions</hi> among our ſelves; theſe are no leſs to be bewailed by us than any other thing whatſoever: both as a calamity, and as one of thoſe ſins, thoſe moſt <hi>grievous and many ſins;</hi> which muſt be acknowledged to be the main cauſe of all our dangers.</p>
            <p>And they are ſo great, that, in humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they can by no other means be remedied, than by the ſpecial hand of Heaven. Which we come therefore here to implore, in a <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bleſſing upon the conſultations and endeavours of the great Council of the Kingdom; and in defeating the wicked counſels and devices of our enemies; and uniting the hearts of all his Majeſties loyal Proteſtant Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59159:37"/>
But theſe great Bleſſings we cannot reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hope to obtain, no not by our Faſting and Humiliation and Prayers; unleſs we endeavour a true reconciliation with God: by being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly penitent; and reſolving to forſake thoſe ſins, which we our ſelves confeſs have brought us into ſuch diſtreſſes and perplexities, as nothing elſe can remedy.</p>
            <p>Now in order unto this, As I excited you, on the laſt Day of ſolemn Faſting and Prayer, to a ſerious and ſpeedy Repentance; by ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as I found in thoſe words of our Saviour, to another of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ii. 16. <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and fight againſt thee with the ſword of my mouth:</hi> ſo at this time I ſhall direct you a little in the way and method of repentance; and point at ſome things of which you are to repent: from theſe words which I have read out of our Saviour's Letter, to the Church of <hi>Sardis;</hi> with whom we of this Church have too manifeſt a reſemblance.</p>
            <p>For as our bleſſed Lord complains (<hi>ver.</hi> 1.) we <hi>have a name that we live, i. e.</hi> are good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: but alas! in deed and truth <hi>are dead;</hi> for we produce not the fruits of Chriſtian vertue. There is a great deal of buſtle and ſtir about Religion, for which we ſeem to be mightily concerned: but the inward life and power of it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59159:38"/>is generally wanting, which we do not love to be troubled withal. Nay, we can ſcarce ſay ſo much of our people as God doth of <hi>Judah</hi> in the firſt <hi>Leſſon</hi> for Evening Prayer (lviii. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.) <hi>They ſeek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a Nation that did righteouſneſs and forſook not the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of their God,</hi> &amp;c. (which alas! we have moſt openly deſerted) though this was far ſhort, we find in that Chapter, of making them an acceptable Nation to him. At the beſt we muſt confeſs we are fallen aſleep and grown very ſlothful, as our Saviour here ſuppoſes (<hi>ver.</hi> 2.) them of <hi>Sardis</hi> to have been: and there is ſo great and univerſal a decay of true piety and goodneſs among us; that we are in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent danger to loſe the ſmall remainders of it. Something good there is ſtill left in this Church, as there was in that: but far from that intire and compleat obedience, which our Lord expects from us; as will appear by conſidering what is to be done by us, for our recovery to a better condition.</p>
            <p>And there are <hi>three</hi> things which our Lord here requires of them in my Text: and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon every one of us, as our neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duty, if we would be ſaved from our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent danger.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59159:38"/>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>To remember what they had received and heard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>To hold it faſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>To repent;</hi> of their forgetfulneſs, I ſuppoſe, their looſeneſs and indifferency in their Religion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall treat of them all in the order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſtand: and conſider them, both with reſpect to the condition of that Church, to whom they were firſt delivered; and then with reſpect to ours, who have no leſs need of ſuch admonitions.</p>
            <div n="1" type="consideration">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> of them ſuppoſes, That they had been taught ſome Doctrin: which they had <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> and entertained with belief; and had <hi>heard</hi> it alſo often ſince inculcated and preſſed (ſo I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the words) by thoſe Paſtors who were ſet over them by the Apoſtle, or thoſe who firſt delivered the Truth unto them. Which was nothing elſe but the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> of which I muſt not here ſpeak at large; but only tell you, It is <hi>that way of ſerving God, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in the Books of the New Teſtament.</hi> Wherein we now <hi>read,</hi> what they then <hi>received</hi> by word of mouth from the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59159:39"/>Apoſtles; and underſtand fully what we muſt believe and do to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Now as there is no cauſe to which God more frequently aſcribes the ſins, and particularly the Idolatry of the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> than their <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> of Him, and of his Law, and of what He had done for them: ſo this very thing (ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid forgetfulneſs and neglect of what Chriſt and his Apoſtles delivered, by Signs and wonders and mighty deeds) introduced that deadneſs in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, of which our Saviour complains in the beginning of this Chapter; and He foreſaw would bring in all the corruptions which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards followed in the Church, and began very early to appear in the Chriſtian World. For there aroſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> nay di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>Antichriſts</hi> (as this very Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> tells us) men who denied the only Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that brought in damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies, ſleighted the authority of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, turned the Grace of God into laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; nay, brought back the old Idolatry, as you read in the foregoing Chapter of this Book, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.20.</p>
               <p>And though this Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> is not charged with ſo deep a degree of Apoſtaſie, as thoſe of <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira;</hi> yet there was great danger of falling into it, unleſs they took
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59159:39"/>this advice of our Saviour, to <hi>remember</hi> (better than they had done) what they had received and heard. Which is the very ſame with that, which God himſelf had given of old to the Iſraelites, to prevent their defection from Him, (in many places of the Book of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> viii. 1, 2, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and which his Prophets were wont to give, in after times, as the firſt ſtep to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, when they had revolted from God their Saviour, xlvi. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8, 9. vi. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5. Who here calls upon his Church in like manner, to bring to remembrance, and think again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, till they had fixed it in their mind, what they had received; and with what affection alſo they had embraced the Goſpel of God's Grace (for that may be implied in the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>how</hi> you have received and heard) as the only means to preſerve them from lapſing farther into a worſe condition, and loſing that good which was ſtill remaining, but ready to dye among them. This the Apoſtles afterward endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great care and diligence, and promiſed as we read in St. <hi>Peter</hi> (2. i. 12, 13, 15.) to endeavour that after their deceaſe, they might <hi>have thoſe things in remembrance always,</hi> which they had been taught: But for want of the like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and watchfulneſs in the people (who did not take ſuch heed as they ought to have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59159:40"/>done to theſe admonitions) the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in proceſs of time, was ſo adulterated, that a great part of the Church fell into that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable apoſtaſie, which is foretold and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in this Book of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> and which we ſee now fulfilled too plainly in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and thoſe of its Communion.</p>
               <p>Which have ſo far degenerated from the primitive Chriſtianity (ſuch is the miſchief of not reflecting perpetually, upon what was firſt delivered and received) that their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on looks more like the old Paganiſm, revived in a new ſhape; than that good old way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God, which our Saviour taught, when He came to deſtroy the works of the Devil. And they were ſtill plunging themſelves fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into ſuch groſs Superſtitions, as endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the very Being of Chriſtianity, (by magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> and St. <hi>Francis</hi> to ſuch a degree, that they were regarded more than Chriſt himſelf) that a Reformation became abſolutely neceſſary; and was generally deſired, as it were eaſie to ſhew, by men of the greateſt note, in theſe parts of Chriſtendome, for choiſe learning and piety.</p>
               <p>Nay, in that very Council, which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves packt to hinder the Reformation (that of <hi>Trent</hi> I mean) Ten ſeveral Kingdomes and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59159:40"/>States, deſired both by their Ambaſſadors and Prelates, That the <hi>Cup in the holy Communion</hi> might be reſtored to the people: from whom it had been ſacrilegiouſly taken; to the manifeſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Chriſtian Religion, which had inſtituted it in both kinds. And many preſſed for <hi>Divine Service in a known tongue;</hi> the want of which was another palpable corruption, and ſhameleſs abuſe in the Roman Church. Which many deſired might be reformed in other Particulars: but nothing could be obtained from them who were reſolved to baffle all theſe pious endeavours. In order to which, they took ſuch a courſe, that there were more <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhops in that Council, who would vote as they were directed (ſometime more by <hi>twenty,</hi> ſometime by an <hi>hundred</hi>) than there was of all the World beſide. So that, in effect, all theſe Parts of Chriſtendom would have reformed, had not <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> oppoſed it; and craftily combined by all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of artifices to hinder theſe honeſt intentions.</p>
               <p>Which, bleſſed be God, prevailed notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in this Church: and were ſo zealouſly and yet ſo prudently proſecuted, that we were happily purged, by the ſingular Grace of God to us, from all thoſe corruptions, which had infected the Body of Religion; without the loſs of any part of that Truth, which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59159:41"/>and at firſt <hi>received.</hi> For when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, we did not ſet up a new Religion, as they falſely and fooliſhly accuſe us; but only caſt out their novel errours, and reduced all things to the ancient Standard or Rule of Faith, and Worſhip, which <hi>was once delivered to the Saints;</hi> that is, to the Church of Chriſt. As will appear by applying all this to our ſelves, and <hi>remembring</hi> you, as briefly as I can, what it is, that we <hi>received,</hi> and have often ſince <hi>heard,</hi> to be the true Doctrine of Chriſtianity, as it ſtands reformed from the corruptions and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Roman Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Which is no other than that, which the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> and all the reſt at firſt received; The fundamental Principle of our Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, That <hi>all things neceſſary to be believed and done for the obtaining ſalvation, are contained and plainly enough expreſſed in the holy Scriptures.</hi> A <hi>Compendium</hi> of which, as to matters of Faith, is drawn up in the Apoſtles Creed (as it is explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the famous Council of <hi>Nice</hi>) which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all things that are neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, in order to eternal life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet we acknowledge that it is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as you have often heard, to believe: but though our ſincere profeſſion of Faith, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what is revealed in the holy Scriptures,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59159:41"/>and comprehended in the Creed, do enter us into the ſtate of Juſtification; yet the fruits of Faith in a godly life, are abſolutely neceſſary to continue us in it. For that very Faith which juſtifies us, doth imply and include in it a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and is accompanied with a promiſe of holy obedience: Which if it be not performed, we cannot be accepted with God, nor claim the promiſe of eternal life.</p>
               <p>This is another Principle, which we have <hi>received.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And among the reſt of the duties which are required of us by our Faith, the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures teach us this, as plainly as any whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; That Chriſtian People ought to have a great regard to their Paſtors; the Guides and Conductors of their Souls in the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: whoſe ſpiritual authority over them is to be reverenced; though not as infallible, yet as moſt valuable; not to be followed blindfold, but fit to be conſulted on all occaſions, and moſt to be relied on in dubious caſes.</p>
               <p>There is no principle of the Reformation more undoubted than this; That a Pilot is not more neceſſary in a Ship, or a Shepherd to watch over the Flock, than ſuch ſpiritual Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Guides are to teach, direct and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern Chriſt's Church; and that among other
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59159:42"/>means and helps which Chriſtian people ſhould uſe to underſtand the Scriptures, the direction of their Guides is the chief. To whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, as to receive men into the Church by Baptiſm, ſo, after they are thus born again, to breed them up in their Religion, as their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Parents; to expound and interpret to them the holy Writings; and out of them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the ignorant, convince Gainſayers, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the peoples miſtakes, reprove their ſins, ſtir them up to all the Duties of a holy life, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſcrupulous, cenſure the contumacious, abſolve the penitent, and adminiſter comfort to dejected Spirits.</p>
               <p>The people indeed ought to examine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the things they deliver out of the Scripture be ſo or no (as the <hi>Beroeans</hi> did and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for it, xvii. <hi>Acts</hi>) and conſcientiouſly to diſcern between truth and falſhood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the right faith and rule of life propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them by their Paſtors, and the poyſoned Doctrine of Hereticks and Deceivers: But they muſt not judge alone, without their direction and guidance; nor haſtily conclude their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to be in the wrong; nor raſhly diſſent from them and refuſe to follow their direction; but rather ſuſpect themſelves, and enquire fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when they think they ought not to aſſent
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59159:42"/>to them; and in the iſſue, if the things they deliver be not plainly againſt the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to ſuſpect their own judgments, rather than contradict thoſe, whom God, without all doubt, hath appointed to be their Inſtructors and Guides.</p>
               <p>By which principle we have quite ſhut out the Roman tyranny on one hand; who would lead the people blindfold, whereas we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make them ſee, and require them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their eyes, and ſhow them that we do not miſlead them: and avoided alſo, on the other hand, the wild frantick liberty of thoſe, who will not be led at all; but go alone, and guide themſelves by their own private judgment. As by the other principle alſo (of ſticking to the Scriptures in all things neceſſary to ſalvation) we have cut off all the fond Traditions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church (which they have equalled with the Scriptures) and yet have retained many things of ancient obſervation, which were not abſolutely neceſſary, but not ſinful; for peace and decency ſake. Becauſe we would not ſeem to have undertaken the work of Reformation, out of any deſire of novelty: but merely to diſcharge our duty to God; in avoiding all things contrary to his Word, and doing all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it. Which made our Reformers,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59159:43"/>for the preſervation, as much as was poſſible, of peace and unity (which the holy Scriptures ſo much commend and enjoyn) to take great care, not to depart any further from any practice of the Church; than it had departed from Chriſt the Founder of it, and from the holy Scriptures whereby it ought to have governed it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus I have, in as few words as I could, told you what it is that we have <hi>received.</hi> From whence we may learn, both how happy we ſhould have been, had we always ſtuck to it, and never deviated from it; (ſo happy, that we ſhould neither have had the Diviſions that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, nor any thing elſe which we come this day to bewail) And alſo how foully the Roman Church hath prevaricated and departed from the ſimplicity of the Chriſtian Religion; <hi>Firſt,</hi> By adding many other Articles of Faith, to thoſe which were at firſt received; and <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> By forbidding the people to look into the holy Scriptures, which contain the foundation and rule of Chriſtian belief.</p>
               <p>Let me touch a little upon theſe two; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the conſideration of our own condition till afterward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſay, It is apparent they have highly offended God, and abuſed his people, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a new Creed, and that contrary to a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59159:43"/>known Decree of the <hi>third</hi> General Council (that at <hi>Epheſus</hi>) which they pretend to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For It ordained that it ſhould <hi>not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any perſon to bring forth, write or compoſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Faith than that which was defined by the holy Fathers, gathered together in the Holy Ghoſt, at the City of</hi> Nice: <hi>and that whoſoever ſhould dare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or offer another Faith, or propound it, to ſuch as were deſirous to be converted to the knowledge of the Truth, either from among the Gentiles, or the Jews, or from any Hereticks; they ſhould, if they were Biſhops or Clergy-men, be depoſed from their Office; if Lay-men, be anathematiz'd.</hi> And yet they of <hi>Rome</hi> have not feared to violate this Decree, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a new Faith; not in words merely, but in ſenſe: about <hi>the adoration of Images, of Saints, of the Euchariſt;</hi> and concerning the <hi>Authority of the Pope,</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and the reſt of the Articles of the new Creed, preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made by the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some of which are of ſuch dangerous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that learned men among themſelves (<hi>Gerſon, Eſpencaeus,</hi> and others) have confeſſed it, among the vulgar, to be no leſs than Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrical: and others doubt not to adde that it is no better among the learned. And others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain are ſo far from being Articles of Faith, that for ought we can find in the Scriptures (or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59159:44"/>true Antiquity) they are not ſo much as proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinions. For inſtance, the <hi>Authority of the Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Monarchy</hi> (as now they fear not to call it) which he pretends to over the whole Church; is founded merely in pride and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and as it was acquired, ſo it hath been ſupported and enlarged (and is ſtill maintained) <hi>by rebellion, treaſon, murthering of Princes, wars, diſpenſing with perjuries and inceſtuous marriages, ſpoils and robberies of Churches and Kingdoms, worldly craft and policy, force and falſhood, forgery, lying, diſſimulation and groſs hypocriſie;</hi> as may eaſily be made good in every particular, to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all thoſe, who have not their eyes blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the God of this World. Who by ſuch villainies hath mightily diſgraced Chriſtianity: which for many Ages was wholly unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any ſuch Faith.</p>
               <p>And there are alſo common opinions that paſs among them uncontradicted, as ſtrongly believed as any Article of Faith; which, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their ſeeming zeal for good works, utterly overthrow any neceſſity of them. For it is the avowed Doctrine of the greateſt Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in that Church, That <hi>though a man live and dye without the practice of any Christian Vertue, and with the habit of many damnable ſins unmortified; yet if he have ſorrow for ſin, and joyn Confeſſion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59159:44"/>with it, and receive abſolution in the laſt moment of his life, he ſhall certainly be ſaved.</hi> And accordingly we ſee, that if the lewdeſt perſons among us will but be reconciled to the Roman Church on their death-bed; they abuſe them with the hope of ſalvation: telling them there is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in our Church, though they were never ſo good; but in theirs there is, though they are never ſo bad. Which is a clear demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That all their diſcourſe about good Works is a mere ſhow; and that Faith alone among them is thought ſufficient to do the buſineſs; and that it is <hi>their</hi> Prieſts, not <hi>Ours,</hi> who teach men to rely upon a naked Faith, and preſume to be ſaved by it.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of all which is their neglect of the rule of Faith, the holy Scriptures; which are ſo much againſt them, that they dare not truſt the people with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That's the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing I noted, as a manifeſt declaration of the corruption of the Roman Church; that they will by no means conſent the people ſhould look into thoſe Books, which contain the Doctrine at firſt received: but upon the ſevereſt penalties, forbid (without a ſpecial Licence obtained) their peruſal of them; as if theſe were the moſt ſuſpected or dangerous of all other Books; or as if it were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59159:45"/>the people ſhould believe the Church, without knowing what the Church ought to believe.</p>
               <p>There is not a more evident token of their guilt than this. For that it is done on purpoſe to keep the people in ignorance, not to preſerve them within the bounds of ſobriety (which may be done by other means) is apparent from hence: that even thoſe ſelect portions of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which they have choſen to be read in the Church publickly; they will not let the people hear in a language which they underſtand. For which no reaſon can be alledged, but that now mentioned, they are loth the people ſhould be acquainted with any thing, that may enlighten their eyes to ſee the errours of that Church. For <hi>Latine Prayers</hi> indeed, wherein they ſpeak to God, they have this excuſe, That God underſtands all languages: but for <hi>Latine Chapters</hi> of the Bible, wherein God ſpeaks to men, there is nothing to be ſaid; the end of ſpeaking to others being that we may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Why then ſhould God be as a Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to his people, ſpeaking to them in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue? And why ſhould thoſe things which in other caſes would be held ridiculous, and contrary to common ſenſe; be eſteemed good and convenient in Religion? Without all
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59159:45"/>doubt ſuch things as theſe are the ſport of the Devil: who hereby hath expoſed Chriſtianity to ſcorn, and both kept the people from being inſtructed by God their Saviour, and delivered them up to be moſt groſly abuſed by evil men.</p>
               <p>For this miſchief is not ſingle, but hath bred and brought forth another; they having ſet up the device of entertaining the people with <hi>Images,</hi> which they call the Books of the Ignorant (and are the means of keeping them in ignorance) inſtead of the holy Scriptures, which are able to make men wiſe to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>For all which the holy and reverend Name of the <hi>Church,</hi> and its infallibility, is uſed for a colour. By which they mean only the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church:</hi> which being but a particular Church, not the univerſal, is become Judg in her own Cauſe: and maintains ſhe does well, nay cannot erre; becauſe ſhe ſays ſhe cannot do otherwiſe. There is no man, who will take the liberty to conſider, that can think this the way of ſalvation. No, it is the manifeſt method of periſhing without remedy; for any thing that the people of that Church can know. For they, being taught ſimply to believe in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to depend wholly upon its authority, without any other enquiry, can never be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59159:46"/>whether this Church, wherein they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, teaches the true and pure Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus, the Lord and Spouſe of the Church. For they are deprived of all means to find this out; being forbidden to look into the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, where Chriſt hath delivered his mind unto us. <hi>All the Faith therefore of the poor people of the</hi> Roman Church, <hi>is no other than a humane Faith; being grounded wholly on the authority of men: and of all humane Teſtimony they rely upon the moſt uncertain,</hi> viz. <hi>that which they give of themſelves.</hi> For they believe their Church to be good, merely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe She ſays ſo: that is, make her judge in her own caſe, which is like to produce the moſt partial Judgment of all other.</p>
               <p>But it is time to leave the conſideration of their faults in this thing: and, as the duty of this Day requires, to reflect ſeriouſly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially upon our own. Which we ſhall the better do, when I have a little opened the <hi>ſecond</hi> general part of my Text; wherein we ſhall ſee how happy we of this Church might have been; if we had <hi>held faſt</hi> that which we have received.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="consideration">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>For that follows, you ſee, in the Charge gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Church of <hi>Sardis, Remember what thou
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59159:46"/>haſt received and heard, and</hi> HOLD FAST; or keep to it; obſerve it and take care to do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: For that's the end of calling things to mind; that we may not depart from them, if they be of conſequence to our happineſs.</p>
               <p>Such was the Doctrine at firſt delivered by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and (to apply it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our ſelves) ſuch is that which we have received; being the very ſame, as you have heard, with that at firſt delivered. Which we ought therefore to keep moſt ſacredly, and to ſtick to it ſtedfaſtly; never, in the leaſt, warp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it; nor turning aſide, either to the right hand or to the left, from the principles and rules of a Religion, which is ſo well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that it ſtands upon the undoubted word of God our Saviour.</p>
               <p>For, as I have ſhewn you, the Religion which we have <hi>received</hi> and <hi>heard,</hi> is no other than what the holy Scriptures (which all acknowledg to be the word of Truth) teach us to believe and practiſe.</p>
               <p>And is a Religion ſo ſincere, that it teaches the people to read the holy Scriptures; becauſe it is not afraid they ſhould therein read its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: And for that end propounds the Scriptures to them in their own Language; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not in the leaſt aſhamed of any thing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59159:47"/>it bids them believe, nor unwilling to be laid to that rule of righteouſneſs, and examined by it.</p>
               <p>A Religion alſo which, in reading the holy Scriptures, bids the people content themſelves with that which they find there clearly and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently delivered (for that it aſſures them is ſufficient for their ſalvation:) leaving things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure for the exerciſe of the learned; and things not drawn from thence, but from uncertain Traditions, or private Inſpiration, to ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and fantaſtical Perſons.</p>
               <p>A Religion which doth not make Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ignorance, but in knowledge: and yet to keep this knowledge within the bounds of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, directs and enjoyns all private perſons to take heed to the publick Miniſtry of the Church; and all publick Miniſters to ſtudy the Scriptures diligently, and <hi>to teach nothing to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly held and believed</hi> (as one of our ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons is<note n="*" place="margin">1571. Tit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionatores.</note>) <hi>but what is agreeable to the Doctrine of the Old and New Teſtament, and which the Catholick-Fathers, and the ancient Biſhops have collected out of that very Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a Religion alſo, which doth not teach us to rely upon Faith alone; but preſſes the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of good works, far more than the Roman
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59159:47"/>Church doth, whatſoever they falſely pretend: only it teaches that God rewards all the good we do, out of his own free mercy, without any deſert.</p>
               <p>And therefore, inſtead of framing and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning Wood and Stone into the Images of men, and ſetting them up for the people to worſhip; it exhorts men, by all means poſſible, to ſtudy to frame themſelves after the Image of God in righteouſneſs and true holineſs: and to conform themſelves to thoſe excellent patterns of Vertue which the Saints have left us for imitation.</p>
               <p>Inſtead alſo of worſhipping the Sacrament, it teaches us to worſhip the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the holy and reverend uſe of the Sacrament: not uſing it to make Jeſus Chriſt, but to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Him; not to make His Body deſcend from Heaven to us, but to lift up our hearts to Him in Heaven; not to turn the Bread and Wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the natural Body and Blood of Chriſt, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpiritual nouriſhment of our Souls. For it doth not think that Chriſt and the Devil both entred into <hi>Judas</hi> together; or that our Saviour did eat Himſelf; or hath ordered matters ſo, that He may be carried away by a Mouſe, and eaten by his greateſt enemies.</p>
               <p>It teaches none of theſe or any ſuch like ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and incredible things; nor doth it intrench
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59159:48"/>upon any man's civil Rights. But though it bid men reverence and obey their ſpiritual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, yet doth not place any of them above Kings, nor exempt them from their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; much leſs aſcribe a power to them of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them from their Thrones, giving away their Kingdoms, and expoſing them to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered (which the proud Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges) but humbly and meekly declares, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> doth, That <hi>every Soul</hi> (even the greateſt Apoſtle, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> interprets him) <hi>muſt be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay more? It is a Religion which acknowledges no other ſupreme Head of the Church, but Jeſus Chriſt; no other rule of Faith, but his Word; no propitiatory Sacrifice, but his Death; no Purgatory, but his Blood; nor any merits, but his obedience to God in all things.</p>
               <p>A Religion therefore, which hath little of outward pomp and ſhow; but much of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubſtance, life and power: which ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth few Ceremonies, but miniſters abundant inſtructions and conſolations: which attributeth little to diſtinction of meats, but preſcribes faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and abſtinence from all meats whatſoever; and that for an exerciſe of humility and other Chriſtian Vertues, without any opinion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or ſatifaction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:59159:48"/>
And it may be added, That it is a Religion to which the very Papiſts themſelves are indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral ways, for their eaſe from many bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. For it is our Religion, which hath quite ſpoiled the Trade that was driven by <hi>Indulgences;</hi> which was ſo ſhameleſly exerciſed before the Reformation, that Sellers of Pardons went, like Pedlars, from houſe to houſe; and for half a Crown offered to let any man have a remiſſion of all his ſins, and the delivery of a Soul out of Purgatory. Which was the thing that firſt ſtirred up the juſt indignation of <hi>Luther;</hi> to whoſe honeſt zeal they are beholden for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from that impoſture. They are not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed neither as formerly with new <hi>lying Miracles and Apparitions:</hi> which are ſeldom pretended now (thanks be to our Religion for it) in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the many illuſions of this kind in former times. They are free alſo from being perpetually pillaged by divers grievous <hi>exactions,</hi> which their Forefathers in this Kingdom (I could ſhew you) complained of as inſupportable. Nor do their people run with Offerings from one Image to another, ſo faſt as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Religion let them ſee their follies. To ſay nothing of their <hi>Cruſado's</hi> and other things, which it is not eaſie for the Pope himſelf now to gull them withal. Which is to be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59159:49"/>upon the account of our Religion: which hath opened many of their eyes to ſee more er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours among them, than they are willing to confeſs.</p>
               <p>Have we not reaſon then to <hi>hold faſt</hi> ſuch a Religion as this, ſo as neither to part with it, nor to depart from it? If truth had the ſame power over the will that it hath over the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; we could never ſuffer our ſelves to be guilty of either. Nay, the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would condemn their own madneſs, for endeavouring to diſturb this Religion; and to bring back that authority hither, which made ſuch Fools of them.</p>
               <p>But alas! it is too notorious how little hold our Religion hath taken on our hearts. There being ſo many who have revolted if not open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet in their hearts and affections (we have too much reaſon to fear) unto the Romiſh delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And others (I am afraid the moſt) who have <hi>retained</hi> what they <hi>received,</hi> only in part: but let go a great deal of it; to the open diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, manifeſt damage, and almoſt undoing of our Religion.</p>
               <p>Which is the thing I muſt now admoniſh you of; in the laſt part of my Diſcourſe upon theſe words: wherein our Saviour calls upon the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> to <hi>REPENT,</hi> of their
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59159:49"/>not <hi>holding faſt</hi> (that is) <hi>what they had received.</hi> And ſo muſt I now call upon you with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs; it being the particular buſineſs of this Day, and the only thing that can ſave us from periſhing in the Pit which is digged for us by our Romiſh Adverſaries, who have been long plotting (and now have almoſt effected) our deſtruction. Yet I ſhall not expatiate through the whole Doctrin of repentance: but confine my ſelf only to ſuch things, as relate to what hath been already ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="consideration">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>You are not now to learn what it is to <hi>repent;</hi> but only what it is you ſhould <hi>repent of:</hi> that is, be heartily ſorry for, and amend.</p>
               <p>And this alſo is ſoon known; if, in obedience to this admonition, you will but reflect upon what you have <hi>received and heard:</hi> and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what conformity your practice holds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And here let me deal as plainly with you, as becomes my Office, and the ſolemn bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of this Day, and the preſent diſtreſs of this Church and Kingdom: which ſhould awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all men of ſenſe to examine themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe <hi>three</hi> Heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What eſteem is remaining among us of the holy Scriptures; in which are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59159:50"/>as you have heard, all our Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> What fruits our Faith hath brought forth: which the holy Scriptures tell us God expects from us; and are ſo neceſſary that we cannot be ſaved without them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> more particularly, What the beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the people of this Church hath been, and is, towards the Paſtors and Guides of their ſouls: with whom God hath principally intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his holy Oracles.</p>
               <p>If all the Members of this Church, would thoroughly examine themſelves upon theſe Heads, they would find, I fear, too much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="examination">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, I ſhall omit the diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (to uſe no harder word) of one whole Sect of men to the holy Scriptures (which they have in a manner laid aſide, and only accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated the Phraſes of it, to that which they call the light within them) and touch upon ſuch things only as are common to all Parties among us. In which,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We cannot but fear (and with grief of heart it ought to be ſpoken and conſidered) there are great numbers who have no value for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59159:50"/>the holy Scriptures at all: but have quite forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken even Chriſtianity it ſelf, which is therein delivered; ſome the very belief of it, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the profeſſion. This is one of the fearful ſins of this Age; which cries for vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us: and hath encouraged this Plot to bring in <hi>Popery</hi> (that is, <hi>Idolatry and Tyranny</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Which durſt never have ſhown their heads here again, if they had not been embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our Irreligion. And though now we ſeem to be ſtirred up to oppoſe them; yet no Religion will be found an unequal match for ſome Religion: which though a very bad one, is better than none at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> It cannot be denied that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of thoſe, who ſtill, bleſſed be God, believe the holy Scriptures, yet have loſt that high eſteem and affection which our pious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had for them. Or if they have any, it doth not appear by their diligent reading of them; which many have laid aſide. Time was, when they were read and ſtudied with great care and fervent deſire, in the beginning of the Reformation; when every Body that could read, had them in their hands; and ſome had a great deal of them by heart, as the Jew now generally have the principal things in the Old Teſtament. But alas! this ardour ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59159:51"/>and now is in a manner extinct.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſculus,</hi> I remember, complains heavily of it, in his Preface to the Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> many years ago; and we are not grown better, but much worſe, I fear, ſince his days. <q>And what other cauſe, ſaith he, can we give for it, but this; That the greateſt part of thoſe who ſeemed to have given up themſelves to the Truth of God, buſied themſelves in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; not that they might be better by framing their lives according to that rule; but that they might be able to diſpute, and to carp at the old errours and ſuperſtitions? And ſo ſome ran into all manner of wickedneſs; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lickt up their old vomit; others leaving the manifeſt Truth turned to new Sects, which ſprang up; and others became neutral, and fell into perfect indifference: whereby they were diſpoſed to receive any Religion; which the great men of this World ſhould be pleaſed to ſet up, by their Authority.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſad Complaint, with much more that there follows, I wiſh we had no cauſe to renew in this Church: and had not loſt our firſt love to our Saviour, and to his holy Word. Which being diſgraced by the means forementioned, better people have been infected with ſuch a negligence; that few read the holy Scriptures,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59159:51"/>as they were wont heretofore to do: but live, as if they believed the Papiſts ſay true, That the reading of the Scriptures is the cauſe of all the miſchiefs that are befallen us. Nay, the publick reading of them in the Church, is not ſo reverently regarded as formerly it was, and as it ought to be. For there are thoſe that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mind what is read; but look upon that as a vacant time to gaze about them; or to whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and diſcourſe what they pleaſe one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. In times paſt, good people were wont to bring their Bibles along with them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but that now is worn out of uſe, or ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle practiſed, that it looks as if they were as much aſhamed of it, as to appear in an old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, which is held ridiculous.</p>
               <p>Let ſuch things therefore be amended, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, if you mean to ſave your Religion from being deſtroyed by our Romiſh Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: whom we have highly gratified by theſe things, and invited to plot our ruine. Let all men among us become ſerious Believers; and ſhew that they are, by reverencing and reading the holy Scriptures; by frequenting the holy Aſſemblies, and there duly attending to them; by growing truly more knowing in the ground and foundation of our Religion; and taking ſuch care to be acquainted with the Scriptures;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59159:52"/>that this may not be our condemnation, that they lay open before us, and were put into our hands, in a language we could underſtand; and yet we deſpiſed them, or would not mind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="examination">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>The miſchief of which is apparent; For if we proceed to examine our ſelves upon the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> Head, we ſhall find a moſt lamentable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count either of our ignorance, or negligence, or wilful diſobedience. For who doth not ſee, that the <hi>Fruits of Faith</hi> are ſo much wanting, that we are in danger to periſh; merely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is ſo little integrity, ſo little common honeſty remaining among us; but ſo much falſeneſs, lewdneſs, filthineſs, and ſottiſh debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, as have made men ſo beyond meaſure dull and ſtupid, that it hath given our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hope, they were diſpoſed to receive any Religion. Nay, they who are better enclined, have been too careleſs in the Divine Service; too frozen in their Devotion; and not ſolicitous enough in the mortifying their unruly affections and paſſions, in bridling their tongues, and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Faith</hi> all thoſe Graces, about which St. <hi>Peter</hi> requires us to <hi>give all diligence,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> i. 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet the Grace of the Goſpel teaches
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59159:52"/>us ſo plainly <hi>how to walk and to pleaſe God;</hi> that it is a wonder every Body does not look upon a holy life, as the moſt neceſſary part of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. For nothing is there ſo earneſtly preſſed as this, which is moſt lacking among us: who live (as it follows there in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ver. 9.) like <hi>blind men,</hi> or (which is all one) <hi>that cannot ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off,</hi> (nothing at a diſtance, but merely that which is held before their eyes) <hi>having forgotten that they were purged from their old ſins:</hi> do not reflect, that is, upon what was done at their Baptiſm; but (as if they were not able to look ſo far back) wallow in their filthineſs which then they ſolemnly renounced.</p>
               <p>But this is too large a Subject for a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Diſcourſe; and therefore I muſt leave it to your own private examination and ſearch; whether you have not relied too much (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what you have received and heard and profeſſed) upon a naked Faith, and the merits of our Saviour; without that care which He requires, to make your Faith work by love to God and to your Neighbours. And here there are as many ſins to be repented of, as there are Chriſtian Duties to be practiſed; if we have been negligent in any of them. And if we will not amend, but ſtill continue to be <hi>barren and unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:59159:53"/>with what reaſon do we expect that He ſhould be pleaſed with an idle Faith, which doth us no good? and not rather look for that doom, which was pronounced upon the empty Fig-Tree; <hi>Cut it down, why cumbreth it the ground?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="examination">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>For the preventing of which dreadful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, I muſt call you to repentance, for one moſt dangerous ſin, contrary to our Faith and Chriſtian Profeſſion: which I fear too many will find themſelves guilty of, if they will but be at the pains to examine the ſtate of their ſouls, upon the <hi>third Head,</hi> viz. <hi>The demeanour of the people, towards their ſpiritual Paſtors and Guides, in the way to ſalvation.</hi> Towards whom there are a great many pious perſons, it muſt be thankfully acknowledged, who ſtill preſerve in their hearts and behaviour, that due regard, which Religion and reaſon require. But it muſt, on the other hand, be bewailed, that there are vaſt numbers, among all ſorts of men, who do not only ſleight them; but have ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off the yoke of obedience to them. Which is the thing above all others, that hath made the Papiſts ſo audacious; and will certainly, if it be not amended, bring in Popery at laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:59159:53"/>
Be not offended, I beſeech you, if in a time when plain dealing is ſo neceſſary, and in a matter of ſuch great conſequence (as I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it) I be ſo bold as to tell you; that there are thoſe who oppoſe themſelves ſo ſenſeleſly, as well as arrogantly, to all ſpiritual Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that this Doctrine of obedience to it they call Popery. Which is a foul reproach to the Reformation; an Apoſtaſie from its Principles; and a caſting off the direction of the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures: which require ſuch obedience as we preach. For we do not bid men follow any Guides, but ſuch as take God for their Guide: that is, guide themſelves and the people, by the Word of God. If we did go about to hide that from the peoples eyes, and hinder them from reading it; it would be an evident ſign that we knew our ſelves to be reproved by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and that inſtead of ſubmitting to that Rule, we would make our own authority to be the ſupreme Rule: which is the crime of the Roman Church. But there is no colour for any ſuch charge to be laid againſt us; who exhort, who preſs the people to be diligent in reading the holy Scriptures: only we deſire them, as the Scriptures themſelves do, that they would take along with them the aſſiſtance and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe, whom Chriſt hath appointed to guide their judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:59159:54"/>
Without which direction men may eaſily ſee, if they pleaſe to read them, what a high crime it is to deſpiſe; and much more to revile and rail at their Authority. And yet ſome have proceeded thus far in their oppoſition to them: nay, deny they have any Authority at all.</p>
               <p>The woful effects of which we ſee, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſo, in the Diviſions that are among us; which have opened a Gap for Popery, and we all fear will bring it in. But we will not ſee, as we ought to do, that all thoſe Diviſions have ſprung from this other Cauſe; and ſtill are maintained and widened, by the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thoſe, whoſe Guidance ought to be religiouſly obſerved: which if we will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, as God commands us, we ſhall inevitably run our ſelves out of our Religion. For our Diviſions (which this Day we come to lament) we all confeſs will do the buſineſs, if they be not cured. And of all the ways of Cure which are now thought of, we ſeem reſolved to wave the principal, if not the only way, of Gods own preſcribing. The method of which I ſhall faithfully and plainly lay before you: that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may judge what is like to become of us, if it be neglected.</p>
               <p>We all grant, I believe, that the right means to avoid or to remedy Contentions and Diviſions
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59159:54"/>in the Church, are as clearly ſet down in the holy Scriptures, as any Rule of life whatſoever. For otherwiſe, they would be extreamly defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in that thing, which is moſt neceſſary, for the preſervation of the Religion which they teach.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Now if you ſearch the holy Scriptures, with never ſo little diligence, you cannot but obſerve there is a Duty frequently inculcated of reverence and obedience to Chriſts Miniſters: which if the people will not pay, (according to the evident meaning of ſuch places, as I ſhall mention anon) it is impoſſible that the Society of the Church ſhould be kept in unity; but muſt neceſſarily break in pieces, and be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt add indeed, That the Miniſters of Chriſt ought alſo to take ſpecial care, to be ſuch wiſe and faithful Stewards in Chriſts houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; that the people may be inclined with the greater forwardneſs to obey their directions. For which end their Duty is no leſs plainly and amply ſet down in the holy Scriptures; and ſuch extraordinary caution is given by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> about the admiſſion of perſons into holy Orders; that were his directions ſincerely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and did the people, as He enjoins, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto them in hearty love and eſteem of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59159:55"/>them for their works ſake; there would be a marvellous encreaſe of Chriſtian knowledg and goodneſs, without that ſtrife and contention which now blaſts them both.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But if Princes do not make ſuch good choice, as they ought, of ſpiritual Governours; or if thoſe ſpiritual Governours, by their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ordain worſe inferiour Miniſters: yet the Authority of ordering or reforming things, doth not, by devolution, come to the people; nor will this juſtifie their diſobedience to them. But their Chriſtian Duty is as manifeſt in this Caſe as in any other; which lyes in theſe two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ought to fall the more earneſtly to their Prayers; both for their King; and for all in authority under him, eſpecially their ſpiritual Paſtors. The Scripture enjoyns both; and the groſs neglect of both, is one cauſe things are no better among us. What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning is there of thoſe words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> ii. 1, 2. <hi>I will that ſupplications,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be made for all men; for Kings, and for all in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty?</hi> And why doth the ſame Apoſtle frequently deſire the Church would <hi>be helping by Prayers for him,</hi> (who needed them leſs than we do) but to teach all Chriſtians how earneſtly they ſhould recommend thoſe to Gods
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59159:55"/>guidance, who are to guide them? Read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> i. 11. vi. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 19. and other places.</p>
               <p>And if they find that their prayers are inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; there being no amendment in thoſe that ſhould take care of them; their Duty <hi>(Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly)</hi> is to examine ſeriouſly, and lay to heart the cauſe why they cannot prevail: and a little conſideration will teach them, that, in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, it proceeds from their own ſins, who deſerve no better Governours and Paſtors. For (as the Prophet ſpeaks in the next Chapter to the <hi>ſecond</hi> Leſſon for Evening Prayer, lix. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1, 2.) <hi>The Lord's hand is not ſhortened, that He cannot ſave; neither his ear heavy, that He cannot hear: but your iniquities have ſeparated between you and your God; and your ſins have hid his face from you, that He will not hear.</hi> And for what ſins do you think, it is more probable, that God is angry with us in this Nation, and will not hear the prayers of this people; than their diſeſteem of Chriſts Miniſters (even of the beſt of them) their contempt of their Office; their proneneſs to diſobedience; nay their ſcurrility and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at all ſpiritual Authority; and ſuch like ſins, expreſly forbidden in Gods holy Word? With which this Church, alas! abounds a great deal more, than with ſupplications and prayers to God for them. All are more forward to find
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59159:56"/>fault (if not to rail and revile) than to beſeech God of his infinite mercy, to give them Paſtors after his own heart: or to examine their own Conſciences how they have provoked God, by their unprofitableneſs, at leaſt, under the beſt means of Grace that He hath beſtowed upon them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But let us ſuppoſe further, That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Paſtors of the Church, are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly negligent; but exceed the bounds of their Authority, as it ſeems to the people, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning things which they take to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: yet this will not warrant their contempt of their Authority, and their caſting off all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them. But <hi>two</hi> things are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; Whether they be certain the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of their Governours are unlawful; or they only fear they are. In the firſt Caſe indeed, they ought not to be obeyed in ſuch things; but by the peoples care to obey in all others, which they judge to be lawful, they ought to demonſtrate that it is only reſpect to God, which makes them not comply in things which ſeem to them to be apparently unlawful. And ſo unity in moſt things being preſerved, they will be the eaſier brought to ſee their errours, on one ſide or other. But in the other caſe, when they are not certain the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59159:56"/>are unlawful (which is the common cauſe of all our Diviſions) but only ſuſpect them to be ſo; it ſeems to be reaſon that the people ſhould not diſobey a certain Command of God (which requires them to ſubmit to their Governours) when they are not certain there is a cauſe for their refuſal. The moſt that can be allowed them is, humbly to deſire thoſe Laws may be altered; or if the Rulers of the Church (who are the proper Judges of ſuch matters) cannot think it ſafe to make ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations as are deſired, then barely to ſuſpend their obedience, in what they fear is unlawful, till they can be better ſatisfied; but fearing withal it may prove a ſin not to obey, to uſe all means for ſatisfaction: not abſolutely deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience (much leſs reviling their Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or making violent oppoſitions to them; which commonly ends in wreſting all authority out of their Paſtors hands) but merely not doing for the preſent what is enjoyned; modeſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating their forbearance in ſuch matters; or, if it cannot be obtained, peaceably and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſubmitting to their cenſures. Which, ſure, would not be heavy upon ſuch humble, modeſt, and truly conſcientious Chriſtians (if they ſhould, God would judge ſuch Governours for their unreaſonable ſeverity) but there
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59159:57"/>would rather be ways found out, to make up the difference, without taking their Paſtors power from them, and governing themſelves as they pleaſe. For God, I am confident, would enlighten the one or the other; to ſee either their errour in enjoyning, or in not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And this that I have ſaid, is the leaſt that can be meant in ſuch places of Scripture as theſe, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> v. 12, 13. <hi>We beſeech you, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know</hi> (that is to love) <hi>them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you. And to eſteem them highly in love for their works ſake: and to be at peace among your ſelves.</hi> (Which they could not fail to be, as long as they kept cloſe to their ſpiritual Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Governours.) And xiii. <hi>Heb.</hi> 17. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your ſouls,</hi> &amp;c. And 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> v. 5. <hi>Likewiſe ye younger, ſubmit your ſelves unto the Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where <hi>firſt</hi> obſerve the name given to the Paſtors of the Church, <hi>viz. Elders:</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports an Office and Authority in the language of all Nations: and here in St. <hi>Peter</hi> implies ſo high an Authority in the Rulers of the Church, that the Apoſtle ſuppoſes more danger of its growing too imperious, than of its being ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59159:57"/>and diſobeyed. For he requires the Elders to <hi>feed</hi> (that is govern, as well as teach) <hi>the Flock of God, not as Lords of Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the Flock,</hi> ver. 2, 3. Which Caution againſt domineering, and <hi>Lording it</hi> (as we ſpeak) had been idle; if the power of the Paſtors, and the obedience due and paid then to it, had not been ſo great, that it might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily grow extravagant: ſuch was the reverence they had to their Perſons, and deference to their Judgments, and ſubmiſſion to their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>For the word <hi>ſubmit</hi> you may obſerve fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is the very ſame whereby he expreſſes (in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 13.) the obedience he would have them give to Kings and thoſe in Authority under them. And therefore cannot ſignifie leſs, than that their directions ought to be followed, and the Flock ruled by their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in all things where God hath not ordered otherways; and that they ſhould be afraid to offend them by diſobedience, and much more by ſhaking off ſubjection to them, and denying their Authority.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Which includes in it a power of ordaining and conſtituting the manner of performing the Service of God according to His Word: which requires that <hi>all things be done decently and in order,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:59159:58"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xiv. 40. The things themſelves to be done (which that place ſpeaks of) are many of them ſpecified in that very Chapter; and the reſt in other parts of the holy Scripture: but the decent manner, form and order how they ſhall be done is no where particularly defined there. And therefore, though by virtue of this Precept no Body hath power to form new Articles of Faith, new Objects of Worſhip, new Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (wherein the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath abuſed her power) yet the ſubſtance of Religion being thus preſcribed in His Word, the order, diſpoſition, form and manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Duties of Religion, is left hereby to be determined by the wiſdom of the Governours of the Church, according to the general Rules of the holy Scripture. Which they cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed enact into Laws, binding by civil penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; yet no Chriſtian Magiſtrate (to whom that power belongs) ever denied them a dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power in making Rules for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, or at any time made them without them; but always took their advice in ſuch matters. For who ſo well able to tell, as they, what is moſt conſonant to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, profitable for their Flock, and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to what hath been practiſed in the Church of God. Which always taught (and it is as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59159:58"/>undoubted a principle of the Reformation as any other) That where the holy Scriptures have not given particular directions for the decent performance of the Duties, they call for (as it was impoſſible they ſhould for all Caſes, Times and Countries) there the Miniſters of Chriſt, whom the holy Scriptures appoint to be the Governours of His Church, are to draw up Orders and Rules, agreeable to the general Rule, which the people ought to obſerve.</p>
               <p>And it is very reaſonable to interpret the place of the Apoſtle before mentioned, in this manner, <hi>Let all things be done,</hi> firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>decently,</hi> or honeſtly; after a comely beſeeming faſhion; with ſuch Rites as will procure venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to holy things, at leaſt ſecure the ſervice of God from contempt, and promote devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the people: and the way to have things done with ſuch gravity, as this word imports, is <hi>next</hi> to do them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>according to order;</hi> or by the deliberate appointment of thoſe, who have authority to ordain ſuch Rites, as will become holy actions. An example of which we have in that very Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. where even ſuch as had extraordinary ſpiritual giſts, are required to ſubmit to this Order. For <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>are ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> That is, there was ſuch a ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59159:59"/>in that Order of men; that when one was propheſying, he was to ceaſe, if a ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Prophet commanded him ſilence.</p>
               <p>Which, among other places of Scripture, might ſilence thoſe, who queſtion the authority of the preſent Governours of our Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their ſuperiority over other Miniſters. Or it might be ſufficient to make them modeſt in this thing, to ſay only this; That Chriſt ſure did not leave His Church without a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (which had been to leave no Church) and that it is incredible the whole Church, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and people ſhould agree to change His Government (without any contradiction that we can find) into this which we have, if this be not it which He left. And that I think hath been as little (nay leſs) queſtioned, as any Point of Chriſtianity: which muſt needs weigh much with all conſiderate minds.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Who likewiſe cannot but grant, that things being thus ordered and appointed by the Authority of Chriſts Miniſters; thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, in all reaſon, ought to be obeyed by thoſe who are ſubject to them; and not left at liberty whether the people will obſerve them or no.</p>
               <p>This is moſt judiciouſly handled by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> in the <hi>Tenth</hi> Chapter of the <hi>Fourth</hi> Book of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59159:59"/>his Inſtitutions; which is well worth the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by every Body: particularly from the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section to the end. Where he bids thoſe who gainſay this and make oppoſition to it, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>how they will approve their moroſeneſs to God. For us it is ſufficient, that we have no ſuch cuſtom of contending, neither the Churches of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. If we be really deſirous then to make peace and reſtore unity in the Church (which is now ſo neceſſary that we are undone without it) this is the firſt thing wherein we ought all to unite, <hi>in repenting of the breach which hath been made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us;</hi> by ſlighting our Guides; by caſting off the Government of the Rulers of the Church, and deſpiſing, nay reviling their Orders.</p>
               <p>I know how difficult it is to perſwade men to this, becauſe they throw the guilt off from themſelves, and ſo confidently lay it all upon their Governours; that it is now generally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for granted, without any doubt, they are in fault, not the people who ought to ſubmit to them. But a very little humility and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty (not to ſay common fenſe) might teach us to make the favourable preſumption on the ſide of Authority: and diſpoſe the people to think, it is more likely that they are miſtaken, than their Guides. Who ought indeed to have nothing ſo much in their thoughts, as how to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59159:60"/>do ſervice to Chriſt, honour to his Religion, good to ſouls, by promoting ſincere piety; and if they have been negligent in this, deeply to humble themſelves before God, and ſtudy to be enſamples to the Flock of ſerious Repentance: But if they fail in this, I am ſure the people can never give a good account of their throwing off the yoke of obedience to them, ſpurning at their Authority, and ſeparating from Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them. The miſchievous effects of which, if nothing elſe, one would think, ſhould be ſufficient to move them to Repentance.</p>
               <p>That is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> To be heartily ſorry for the breach they have made; and reflect upon it as the original of all our miſeries. And <hi>then</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God moſt earneſtly to forgive it; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that open jeſting, nay ſcoffing (which hath been ſo rife among us) at all ſpiritual Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which, in the next place, let every one of us ſeriouſly acknowledge, and reſolve to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſo as to be adviſed by them; and take great heed to their Counſels and Reſolutions; to weigh them conſiderately; and not lightly and haſtily to depart from them; much leſs riſe up in oppoſition to them; but when you are forced by Gods Command (as you think) to decline obedience in any particular injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be the more careful in obſerving the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59159:60"/>reſt, againſt which you have no exception: and ſtill to reverence their Perſons and their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, when you cannot obſerve their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to ſpeak well of them, and peaceably to diſſent from them; remembring that if they be liable to miſtake, you are much more: and therefore ought not to <hi>be wiſe in your own conceit: but to think ſoberly of your ſelves, as you ought to think.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. This is the way of peace, which we have <hi>received</hi> from Chriſt and his Apoſtles (and I might add all ſucceeding Paſtors in the Church) of which I thought good to <hi>remember</hi> you; and to call you to <hi>repentance</hi> for departing from it; and to exhort all people to return into it: as the only means of our preſervation; and of making the preaching of the Goſpel (if God pleaſes to continue it) effectual for our reformation and amendment, in all other things that are amiſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. For as no Kingdom can ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Religion; ſo no Religion can ſtand long (no not this excellent Religion, which we have received, and I have briefly deſcribed) without a due eſteem of and regard to its Miniſters. In obedience to whom, even they who cannot comply with all publick Orders, will find more true comfort, and more favour alſo with God and men, than in any other way whatſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:59159:61"/>
But here is the miſchief, that it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errour of Mankind, to ſeek that for off, which (as the Lord told his people) is near at hand, within them, even in their heart and in their mouth. if they would be but Doers of His Word, and not Hearers only. They hunt up and down for remedies of their Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but will not mind the obvious Cure, which is laid before them by God himſelf in his holy Scriptures. Where it ſhines clearly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, if mens paſſions did not eclipſe it from them. Which are now ſo great and violent, that it is a ſingular happineſs, if any perſon, in this turbulent Age, can ſee the Divine Truth himſelf, in Points of greateſt moment. But to cauſe others to ſee it, is a matter of ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty that there is ſmall hope of it: whilſt they ſuffer their foul affections and paſſions (like a ſteam from a great many Dunghils) to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt the face of Heaven, whence light ſhould come into their ſouls; and evaporate that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward filth which is lodged in their hearts, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſive language, as it were on purpoſe to choke the good Spirit of God, which breathes in others mouths, whoſe breaſts God hath inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his Grace.</p>
               <p n="10">10. But this muſt not diſcourage Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, nor hinder them from aſſerting their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59159:61"/>which is to rule the people, and not to be ruled by them. To which courſe if we will not ſubmit (when God himſelf ſo plainly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to it) all the ways which humane policy can invent, will prove ineffectual; and never make a laſting union and peace among us: if they make any at all. But after mens ill affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (which they will not root out) have been laid aſleep and ſuppreſſed for a time; they will awake and break out again with the greater vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, and make worſe diſorders: till with the contempt of the Miniſters of Religion, our Religion it ſelf be brought into ſuch contempt; that, as a puniſhment for our diſobedience to juſt Authority, we fall under the tyranny of thoſe, who will uſe no moderation.</p>
               <p>That's the heavy Judgment (I told you in my laſt Faſt-Sermon) threatned before the late Wars, by a great and holy Divine of this Church (ſome of whoſe words I have uſed now and then in this Diſcourſe) for this ſin of diſobedience unto and contempt of, all Eccleſiaſtical Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And whether this ſin be not encreaſed and grown more audacious ſince that time (and conſequently our danger greater) I leave you to conſider and judge. Only let me tell you, That they who ſtand divided from us, complain of it as well as we, finding to their ſhame and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59159:62"/>grief (as an eminent man among them expreſſes it<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> Sacril. deſert. p. 103. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>) that <hi>we are endangered by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, principally becauſe the ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited part of the religious people, will not be ruled by their Paſtors; but muſt have their way, and will needs be Rulers of the Church and them.</hi> The effect of which he tells them is this; <hi>You have made more Papiſts, than ever you or we are like to recover. It is you that tempt them to uſe Fire and Eaggot; that will not be ruled nor kept in concord, by the wiſeſt and holieſt and moſt ſelf-denying Miniſters upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is an ingenuous Confeſſion of the guilt and the danger, we have all run our ſelves into by this ſin: and that though all the blame is now laid at the door of the Rulers of this Church, yet it is ſo unjuſt a Charge; that were they in all points ſuch as thoſe that accuſe them, there would be no end of our troubles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions; unleſs the people, even they that think themſelves moſt religious, will grow leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, and ſubmit to be ruled by their proper Governours. It hath been ſaid indeed, that they do follow ſuch Guides, as they think fit to lead them: but here is one that contradicts it; and complains of their unrulineſs. And beſides, I muſt add, that ſuch Guides ought not to be followed, as will not ſubmit to be governed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59159:62"/>by their Superiours: there being nothing, as I ſaid before, ſo little diſputed in the Chriſtian Religion, as the Authority which the Biſhops exerciſe over the Presbyters in the Church. And if they will not ſo much as give us leave to tell them of this, without incurring their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor patiently bear with thoſe reproofs which we think neceſſary; it is impoſſible they ſhould repent of this ſin, and then our deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is unavoidable.</p>
               <p>This part of my Diſcourſe indeed may ſeem unneceſſary, in an audience where I hope all of you are better affected: but it hath its uſe even among ſuch, as <hi>hold faſt what they have received and heard</hi> concerning this Duty. Who ſhould endeavour by their brotherly reproofs and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent admonitions, to ſtop the progreſs of this Diſeaſe, in thoſe whom they find infected with it. Deſire them to conſider things calmly, and to ſtudy this part of their Chriſtian Duty. Pray them not to be ſo paſſionately bent againſt the means of their ſafety: And that they would at leaſt hear, what Chriſts Miniſters can ſay for themſelves and the Authority he hath left them. Tell them, it is impoſſible any wound ſhould be healed, while the inflammation continues: And that as when a houſe is on fire they that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59159:63"/>ſpeak and give the beſt advice cannot be heard, by reaſon of the noiſe and cries of thoſe who are gathered about it; ſo we ſhall never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one another as long as we are clamorous; nay have our minds violently inflamed with ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and hatred, even againſt thoſe that would cure us of it. The ſtudy of Gods truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a quiet and peaceable Spirit; which deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berates and weighs things, without carping at perſons: and doth not preſently conclude we plead our own private intereſt, when we plead the Cauſe of Chriſts Miniſters. Who do not merely bear teſtimony to themſelves, as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do; but appeal to the holy Scriptures, where theſe things are as plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, as any part of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>God of his infinite mercy touch every heart in this Nation, with a ſenſe of them; that we may not ſhut our eyes againſt the things that belong to our peace; nor while we endeavour an union, make the moſt dangerous rent that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was: But all ſo truly repent of this ſin, that it may be a happy ſtep to the reforming all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that have ſprung from this. Then we need not fear any evil that the Devil or man can plot againſt us: but while we walk in that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order, which Chriſt hath appointed (the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59159:63"/>people being ruled by their Guides, and their Guides ruled by God) may triumphantly ſay (as it is in one of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> appointed for this Day, xlvi.) <hi>We will not fear though the Earth be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and though the Mountains be carried into the midſt of the Sea</hi> (though tumults and hurlibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſhould ariſe, we will not be afraid, for) <hi>God is in the midſt</hi> of this Church, <hi>She ſhall not be moved: God ſhall help her, and that right early.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
